Good afternoon.
下午好。
My name is Sarah.
我叫 Sarah。
And my name is Grant.
我叫 Grant。
And we are the Harvard Crocodillos and the Radcliffe Pitches.
我们是 Harvard Crocodillos 和 Radcliffe Pitches。
Now, Sarah and I understand that today is the final lecture of CS50.
Sarah 和我听说今天是 CS50 的最后一节课。
It's been a tough semester.
这学期过得很艰难。
We made it through p-sets four, five, and even finance.
我们完成了作业四、五，甚至还有金融。
Now, I know this is an unpopular opinion, but I particularly enjoyed finance.
我知道这可能不受欢迎，但我特别喜欢金融。
I spent a lot of time with my flask.
我和我的酒瓶度过了很多时光。
The p-set?
作业？
There was a p-set?
有作业吗？
Well, at least things are looking up.
好吧，至少情况正在好转。
Today is our last lecture, and look how far we've come.
今天是我们的最后一节课，看看我们已经走了多远。
If I were an emoji right now, I'd be the face with tears of joy.
如果我现在是一个表情符号，我会是那个喜极而泣的表情。
Sorry about that. We're just trying to work some CS50 references into the intro.
抱歉，我们只是想在开头加一些 CS50 的梗。
I mean, boy, I sure hope this tide man doesn't run off my Mario filter.
我的意思是，我希望这个 tide man 不会从我的马里奥滤镜里跑掉。
You could say that.
你可以这么说。
For loop x equals open bracket 1 comma 2 close bracket.
for 循环 x 等于开括号 1 逗号 2 闭括号。
Boy, I sure wish we had check 50 to see if these jokes were funny when we wrote them.
我真希望我们有 check50 来看看这些笑话在我们写的时候是否好笑。
Anywho, we hope that you'll enjoy this brief serenade.
无论如何，我们希望你会喜欢这段简短的小曲。
Well, you lace up your boots and you walk on down to a knock-down shack on the edge of town.
你穿上靴子，走到城边一个摇摇欲坠的小屋。
There's a Latin bean combo there that just won't quit.
那里有一支拉丁乐队，永不停歇。
You can walk up to your seat, but the light won't fall in there.
你可以走到你的座位上，但灯光照不到那里。
You take them sights and at the house, the house, the house of blue lights.
你带着这些景象，来到了蓝光之家。
Well, there's fryers, broilers, and detroits.
那里有炸鸡、烤鸡和底特律披萨。
But the trick of the trade is when they're serving up those fine apes.
但他们的拿手好戏是供应上等的猿猴。
You're gonna spend the rest of your brights down at the House of Blue Lights.
你会在蓝光之家度过余生。
Down at the house, the house of blue lights Well, you lace up your boots and you walk on down To a knock-down shack on the edge of town There's a Latin-American combo there
在蓝光之家，你穿上靴子，走到城边一个摇摇欲坠的小屋，那里有一支拉丁乐队，
that just won't quit Keep a-walkin' till you see a blue light lit ball in there And you dig the sights down at the house, the house of blue lights
永不停歇，一直走，直到你看到里面亮起一盏蓝灯，你在蓝光之家欣赏着这些景象。
Doobie dan, doobie doobie doobie, boy.
嘟比丹，嘟比嘟比嘟比，伙计。
Doobie dan, doobie doobie doobie, hi, hi, hi.
嘟比丹，嘟比嘟比嘟比，嗨，嗨，嗨。
Boy, b-boy, b-boy, b-boy, b-boy.
伙计，兄弟，兄弟，兄弟，兄弟。
Boy, b-boy, b-boy, b-boy.
伙计，兄弟，兄弟，兄弟。
Guy, doobie doobie doobie, boy.
伙计，嘟比嘟比嘟比，伙计。
Place up your boots and you walk on down to a knock-down shack on the edge of town.
穿上你的靴子，走到城边一个摇摇欲坠的小屋。
There's a lot of green combo there that you'll swarm with.
那里有很多绿色组合，你会和它们一起狂欢。
Keep a-walkin' till you see a blue light light fall in there.
一直走，直到你看到里面亮起一盏蓝灯。
Can you dig them spikes down at the house?
你能在蓝光之家找到那些尖刺吗？
The House of Blue Lights.
蓝光之家。
Do-do-do-do-do-do-do-ah.
嘟嘟嘟嘟嘟嘟啊。
Be sure to spend your brights down at the House of Blue Lights.
一定要去蓝光剧场挥洒你们的青春。
Good afternoon, everyone.
大家下午好。
We are the Harvard Crocodilos, and it is such an honor to be here with the Radcliffe Pitches performing for CS50's final lecture.
我们是哈佛鳄鱼合唱团，很荣幸能和拉德克利夫合唱团一起，在CS50的最后一节课上表演。
Congratulations to everyone, and we hope you'll enjoy this, our tribute to CS50.
祝贺大家，希望你们喜欢我们为 CS50 准备的献礼。
1, 2, 1, 2, 3, 4.
1，2，1，2，3，4。
C is for the language I once knew.
C 是我曾经熟悉的语言。
O is for all notation I must do.
O 代表我必须做的所有符号。
D is for Dynamic, Flask Run, and Finance.
D 代表 Dynamic、Flask Run 和 Finance。
It E is even more than David Maylin can adore.
E 甚至比 David Malan 更让人喜爱。
So code is all that I can give to you.
代码就是我能给你的全部。
Code, debugging it since P set to.
自从 P 设置好后，一直在编写和调试代码。
Soon deadlines I'll make it.
很快就能赶上截止日期。
Hit compile and please don't break it.
点击编译，请别出问题。
Code was made by me for you.
代码是我为你而写。
Once new, O is for notation, I must do.
曾经是新的，O 代表符号，我必须做。
D is for dynamic, Flastra and Finance.
D 代表 Dynamic、Flask 和 Finance。
C is even more than David Malan can adore.
C 甚至比 David Malan 更让人喜爱。
So code is all that I can give to you.
代码就是我能给你的全部。
Code me.
给我代码。
Sometimes, deadlines don't make it.
有时候，截止日期是赶不上的。
They come by, but please don't break it.
他们来了，但请别弄坏它。
No, what's made might be for you.
不，也许是为你准备的。
C is for the language.
C 代表这门语言。
0 1 0 0 0 1 0 0.
O is for O notation.
O 代表 O 符号。
0 1 0 0 0 1 0.
D is for dynamic, flask run, and finance.
D 代表动态的，flask run，还有金融。
And E is even more than David Maylin can adore.
E 比 David Maylin 喜欢的还要多。
So code is all that I can give to you.
我能给你的只有代码。
All right, this is CS50.
好了，这是 CS50。
And CS50, this was the Harvard Crocodillos and the Radcliffe Pitches.
CS50，这是哈佛鳄鱼队和拉德克利夫皮切斯队。
If one more time, we could thank them for joining us today.
再次感谢他们今天加入我们。
So this is already week 10, our last.
现在已经是第 10 周了，也是最后一堂课。
And indeed, among the goals for today are to hopefully give you all the more of appreciation of truly just how far you've come.
今天目标之一是希望大家都能更加感激自己一路走来的进步。
Recall that in week zero, we began with this visual here, whereby it was described, this class, as a bit of a fire hose.
回想一下，在第 0 周，我们从这张图开始，它把这门课比作消防水带。
Whereby drinking from that fire hose, or really a fire hose from a water fountain, is not unlike getting an education down the road, too.
从消防水带，或者说是饮水机里的消防水带里喝水，和以后接受教育的过程没什么两样。
And so this is to say that if you're feeling like you didn't quite get it all down, that's actually OK, and that's to be expected.
也就是说，如果你觉得你没有完全理解，这很正常，也是意料之中的。
And even if you felt that with each passing week, 0, 1, 2, all the way up now till 10,
即使你感觉每周，从第 0 周，第 1 周，第 2 周，一直到现在的第 10 周，
It never really ever got easier, perhaps.
课程从来没有真正变得更容易过。
Just consider that what was once hard, like Mario and getting Hello World to compile, is indeed the right measure of the delta between week 0 and now in week 10.
想想看，曾经很难的事情，比如 Mario 和编译 Hello World，恰恰是衡量第 0 周和现在第 10 周之间差距的标准。
In fact, you might recall that again in week 0, 2 thirds of your classmates had never taken a CS course before.
事实上，你们可能还记得在第 0 周，你们班三分之二的同学以前从未上过 CS 课程。
Now, of course, you all have.
现在，当然，你们都上过了。
And indeed, if you think back, too, to this final sentiment from week zero, that indeed, what ultimately matters in this course is not where you end up relative to your classmates, but where you end up relative to where you yourself began.
如果你们回想一下第 0 周的最后一句话，这门课最终重要的不是你相对于同学的最终成绩，而是你相对于自己的起点取得了多少进步。
So I would take some pride, take some satisfaction, take some relief, even though a little bit more work does remain, at really just how far you've come since that week zero.
即使还有一点工作要做，我也会为你们从第 0 周开始取得的进步感到自豪、满意和欣慰。
Recall that in week 0, we literally started with just 0's and 1's.
回想一下，在第 0 周，我们真的是从 0 和 1 开始的。
And by now, many of you might have gleaned that these 64 0's and 1's have been spelling something week by week.
到目前为止，你们中的许多人可能已经发现，这 64 个 0 和 1 一周又一周地拼写着一些东西。
In fact, today is our very last message here in binary encoded on stage, but then quickly
事实上，今天是我们最后一次用二进制编码在舞台上传递信息，但很快就会结束。
Basically, we introduced Scratch, and we started to assemble some building blocks of programming, loops, conditions, functions, and the like, but without all the distractions of semicolons and curly braces and all of that, which admittedly we introduced the next week when we introduced you to C.
我们介绍了 Scratch，并开始组装一些编程的构建
块，循环、条件、函数等等，但没有分号、花括号等等的干扰，我们在下一周介绍 C 语言时介绍了这些。
But even now that we've transitioned to Python, hopefully even those kinds of curiosities or confusions are hopefully starting to just get more familiar.
但即使是现在我们已经过渡到 Python，希望即使是那些好奇或困惑也开始变得更加熟悉。
And so you finally start to see the missing semicolon as opposed to spending time on that kind of struggle.
你会开始注意到缺少的分号，而不是把时间浪费在这种斗争上。
Recall, too, that in week two, we started talking already about memory and how you can manage things in arrays that later became, of course, in Python lists.
回想一下，在第二周，我们就开始讨论内存了，以及如何在数组中管理事物，当然，这些数组后来变成了 Python 中的列表。
The week after, we talked not only about debugging bugs in code, but how to debug those same programs.
接下来的一周，我们不仅讨论了调试代码中的错误，还讨论了如何调试这些程序。
Thereafter, we started talking about algorithms.
之后，我们开始讨论算法。
And we took a step back from code.
我们从代码中退后一步。
And looked at the bubble sorts, and the selection sorts, and the merge sorts, and all of the searches as well that go hand-in-hand with that.
看看冒泡排序、选择排序、归并排序，以及所有与之相关的搜索。
And indeed, this ultimately is what a lot of problem-solving moving forward is going to be about, just solving problems with some form of algorithm.
事实上，这就是未来很多问题解决的关键，即用某种形式的算法来解决问题。
And you have so many different languages in your toolkit now with which to approach problems like those.
现在，你的工具包中有这么多不同的语言，可以用它们来解决这些问题。
We talked thereafter about?
之后我们讨论了什么？
Pointers, which are not likely to come back in any modern languages that you now use.
指针，这在你们现在使用的任何现代语言中都不太可能再出现了。
But hopefully, you have all the better of a sense underneath the hood of what's going on inside of the computer.
但希望你们对计算机内部的运作方式有了更好的了解。
So that when you're designing something, you're using something, something crashes, you at least have a mental model for what's going on.
当你在设计东西、使用东西、东西崩溃时，你至少对正在发生的事情有一个心理模型。
And it's no longer that week 0 black box as it once was.
它不再是像曾经那样的第 0 周的黑盒子了。
I mean, you built things like this.
我的意思是，你构建了这样的东西。
Think back to week 5 when you built your own hash table.
回想一下第 5 周，你构建了自己的哈希表。
And those things are everywhere.
这些东西无处不在。
Key value pairs, whether it's in Python,
键值对，无论是在 Python 中，
Or in C, or if it's now in CSS, in JavaScript, and even HTML.
或者在 C 中，或者现在在 CSS 中，在 JavaScript 中，甚至在 HTML 中。
Like that principle of key value pairs is really everywhere.
就像键值对的原理真的无处不在。
And so of course, now code doesn't necessarily have to look like this.
现在代码不一定要像这样。
It now wonderfully looks a little something more like this.
现在它看起来更像是这样。
But eventually, you're probably not.
但最终，你可能不会。
I'm not going to use Python anymore.
我不会再使用 Python 了。
Something new and better is going to come along.
更新更好的东西将会出现。
But odds are, like a lot of the building blocks from these past 11 weeks are still going to be useful for wrapping your mind around those new worlds.
但很有可能，过去 11 周中的许多构建模块仍然可以帮助你理解那些新世界。
And indeed, SQL we introduced you a little bit to.
事实上，我们向你简要介绍了 SQL。
And even if you don't feel yourself yet an expert, hopefully you have a sense of what you can do with it and what problems you can solve.
即使你还不觉得自己是专家，但希望你对你能用它做什么以及能解决什么问题有所了解。
It's, of course, a better alternative to something simple like a spreadsheet.
当然，它是比电子表格这样简单的东西更好的选择。
And now, of course, web stuff is everywhere, whether it's on your laptop or desktop or even a lot of the mobile apps that you use on your phone.
现在，网络内容无处不在，无论是在你的笔记本电脑、台式机，还是在手机上使用的许多移动应用程序中。
Even though they're native applications, like you install them from Google Play or the Apple App Store,
即使它们是原生应用程序，比如你从 Google Play 或 Apple App Store 安装的，
Like, they're implemented increasingly with HTML, CSS, and JavaScript, but they're put in a little rectangular window so you don't even notice that that's actually really just an embedded browser.
它们越来越多地使用 HTML、CSS 和 JavaScript 实现，
但它们被放在一个小的矩形窗口中，因此你甚至没有注意到它实际上只是一个嵌入式浏览器。
And then, of course, you can build things, as you might for your final project, that too might very well be web-based if you go that route.
你当然可以构建东西，就像你的期末项目一样，如果你选择这条路，它也很可能是基于网络的。
I mean, I'm still clinging to the very first web app I ever made years ago.
我的意思是，我仍然留恋着几年前我做的第一个网络应用程序。
But honestly, I do that in part because I was just so darn proud that I taught myself how to do something, and it actually worked and was used by other people.
但说实话，我这么做一部分原因是因为我为自己学会了如何做某件事而感到非常自豪，而且它确实有效，并且被其他人使用。
So whether it's just used by you or your classmates or your roommates or your family or your company down the line, there's a great sense of satisfaction that comes despite all of the pain that might be along the way when you just can't see or fix that bug.
无论它是由你自己、你的同学、你的室友、你的家人还是你的公司使用，
当你无法看到或修复那个 bug 时，尽管一路走来可能充满了痛苦，但当你完成时会有一种巨大的满足感。
Now, of course, we'll transition, as you'll see,
当然，正如你将看到的，我们会过渡到
And the coming days to empowering you to code client-side as well.
在接下来的几天里，我们将授权你编写客户端代码。
Up until now, you've been using our own VS Code installation in the cloud, which is nice because you got up and running super fast in week one, focusing only on code challenges, not on technical difficulties. But among the goals now.
到目前为止，你一直在使用我们自己的云端 VS Code 安装，
这很好，因为你在第一周就能快速启动和运行，只专注于代码挑战，而不是技术难题。但现在的目标之一是，
If you so choose and want to program after this class, even if you've never taken another CS course before, you can use these same real-world, de facto standard tools on your own Mac or PC.
如果你愿意，并且希望在这门课之后继续编程，
即使你以前从未上过其他 CS 课程，你也可以在你自己的 Mac 或 PC 上使用这些相同的、现实世界中实际标准的工具。
And so pictured here is a screenshot of VS Code on the Mac.
所以图中显示的是 Mac 上 VS Code 的截图。
And even though, yes, you're going to have to jump through a couple of more hoops to just get Python or some other language working on your own Mac or PC, That's what programming is ultimately going to be about.
是的，你必须克服更多的障碍才能让 Python 或其他语言在你自己的 Mac 或 PC 上运行，但这最终就是编程的意义所在。
And we deliberately transition you to this at terms end so that now you have 11 weeks of more comfort under your belt with which to solve sort of silly technical support headaches that might have been deal breakers so many weeks ago.
我们特意在学期末让你过渡到这一点，这样你就有了 11 周的更舒适的缓冲时间，
可以用这些时间来解决那些在几周前可能会让你崩溃的愚蠢的技术支持问题。
So there's still more to be done in the coming weeks.
所以在接下来的几周里还有更多的事情要做。
And indeed, a support structure, therefore, the CS50 Hackathon, of course, will be this 7 PM till 7 AM opportunity to dive into your final project, well, really,
事实上，因此，CS50 黑客马拉松将从晚上 7 点到早上 7 点，让你有机会深入研究你的期末项目，
Continue diving into your final project, ideally at that point, alongside classmates, perhaps your project partners, if you're working collaboratively.
继续深入你的期末项目，理想情况下，在那时，与同学们一起，也许还有你的项目伙伴，如果你是在合作的话。
And awaiting you will be such memories and excitement, hopefully, as these, even as you then turn your attention back to your final project.
希望你能像这些人一样，在将注意力转回到期末项目的同时，还能回忆起这些激动人心的时刻。
There, of course, will be several meals during the day, culminating with 5 AM shuttles to IHOP, the local pancake place.
当然，在那天会有几顿饭，最后在凌晨 5 点乘坐班车前往当地的煎饼店 IHOP。
If you are so awake at that point, or even if you get there, this is not an uncommon sight, as you might recall from week zero.
如果你那时还醒着，或者即使你到了那里，这也不是什么稀奇的事，你可能还记得在第零周的时候。
And then lastly is the CS50 Fair, which is finally back after a couple of years now of it not being on campus.
最后是 CS50 展览会，在经过几年的校外展览后，它终于回到了校园。
And this will be an opportunity for everyone to present their final projects to passersbys, classmates, faculty, and staff, and really just delight in what it is you created on your Mac, your PC, your phone.
这将是一个让每个人都能向路人、同学、教职工展示他们的期末项目的机会，并真正地为你在 Mac、PC、手机上创造的东西而感到高兴。
In the cloud or anywhere else.
在云端或任何其他地方。
And indeed, it's just going to be an opportunity to bring your laptop to a shared space or your phone and introduce your project to passers by, such as might appear, and ultimately celebrate what you all accomplished.
事实上，这只是一个机会，让你带着你的笔记本电脑或手机到一个共享的空间，
向路人介绍你的项目，比如可能会出现的人，并最终庆祝你们所有人取得的成就。
And indeed, will you be handed at the CS50 fair your very own I took CS50 t-shirt, which I dare say I'm still wearing all of these years later.
的确，在 CS50 展会上，你们会拿到自己的“我参加了 CS50”T 恤，我敢说这么多年过去了，我今天仍然穿着它。
And so you too.
你们也会。
We'll have that ahead of you as well.
我们也会为你们准备好的。
So for what's on the agenda today, we thought we would not only look back but look forward.
今天的议程安排是，我们不仅要回顾过去，还要展望未来。
But first, we wanted to thank so many of the team members that have been helping both on stage and off, who've made this course and these sections and so much more about CS50 possible.
但首先，我们要感谢许多在台前幕后提供帮助的团队成员，是他们让这门课程、这些讨论课以及更多 CS50 的内容成为可能。
Of course, the building that we are now in, there's a whole team downstairs in Memorial Hall who helps us get set up and organized each day.
当然，还有我们现在身处的这栋楼，Memorial Hall 楼下有一整个团队，每天都在帮助我们布置和组织。
Our thanks to them. There's the Education Support Services team, who makes everything look and sound so well down here, especially when we have all of the more microphones as well.
感谢他们。还有教育支持服务团队，是他们让这里的一切看起来和听起来都那么好，尤其是在我们有这么多麦克风的情况下。
Our friends, the Harvard Crocodillos and the Radcliffe Pitches, most recently.
感谢我们的朋友们，最近的哈佛鳄鱼合唱团和拉德克利夫皮彻斯合唱团。
And then, of course, CS50's own team, CS50's own favorite restaurant, Chang Shou, down the road.
当然，还有 CS50 自己的团队，CS50 最喜欢的餐厅，路边的“长寿”。
Indeed, if you find yourself in Cambridge for the next one, two, three, four years, or visiting from out of town, do pay a visit to our friends just down the road.
真的，如果你在接下来的一、二、三、四年里碰巧来到剑桥，或者从外地来参观，一定要去拜访一下我们在路边的朋友们。
And in fact, we'll have our very last CS50 lunch this Friday, if you're able locally. to partake.
事实上，本周五我们将举行最后一次 CS50 午餐会，如果你在本地的话，可以来参加。
And then there's CS50's own team, both on stage and off.
然后是 CS50 自己的团队，包括台前和幕后的。
And my thanks truly, because not only do they make everything run so smoothly, they capture it for students here who might not be physically present here, for our friends down in New Haven at Yale, and certainly for anyone online who might be tuning in as well.
我衷心地感谢他们，因为他们不仅让一切运行得如此顺利，
还为那些可能无法亲临现场的学生、为我们在纽黑文耶鲁大学的朋友们，当然也为任何可能在网上收看的观众们记录下来。
And then lastly, Wanted to thank, of course, the huge team of your classmates, your peers that make CS50 possible in sections, in office hours, tutorials, and more.
最后，当然，还要感谢你们的同学们，你们的同伴们组成的庞大团队，是他们在讨论课、办公时间、辅导课等等方面让 CS50 成为可能。
Allow me to share with you the outtakes so that even we, the teaching staff, sometimes struggle with computer science.
请允许我和大家分享一些花絮，让大家看到，即使是我们这些教职工，有时也会在计算机科学方面遇到困难。
Here are some of the clips that we captured when just passing packets via TCPIP a while back.
以下是一些我们在前段时间通过 TCP/IP 传递数据包时捕捉到的片段。
You saw the nicely polished version.
你们看到的是精心剪辑过的版本。
But here are, if I may, if we could dim the lights, are some of the outtakes.
但如果可以的话，请允许我们将灯光调暗，这里有一些花絮。
Sophie!
Sophie！
Amazing.
太棒了。
That was perfect.
完美。
Bonnie.
邦妮。
I think I... Over to you, LL.
我想... 交给你了。
Guy.
盖伊。
That was amazing.
太棒了。
Thank you all.
谢谢大家。
Indeed, in that moment, if we could, just one round of applause for everyone who's helped out this semester.
确实，此时此刻，如果可以的话，让我们为所有在本学期提供帮助的人鼓掌。
So back in week zero, we introduced you, of course, to this idea of computational thinking, which is to think a little more methodically, a little more algorithmically.
回到第 0 周，我们向大家介绍了计算思维的概念，也就是更有条理、更算法化地思考。
And by way of these various languages, hopefully that is something you notice, maybe not in the moment, but in the months and the years to come, that you do find that your thoughts are indeed a little more cleaned up.
通过学习各种语言，希望你已经注意到了这一点，也许不是现在，而是在未来的几个月甚至几年里，你会发现自己的思维确实变得更清晰了。
And you're just able to express yourself a little more precisely and even spot illogic in someone else's document or statements as well.
你能够更准确地表达自己，甚至能发现别人文档或陈述中的逻辑错误。
But at the end of the day, really, a course like this is also about critical thinking.
但归根结底，像这样的课程实际上也是关于批判性思维的。
And indeed, rewind again to week 0, when we framed the entirety of computer science as really just this, like problem solving.
让我们再次回到第 0 周，当时我们将整个计算机科学概括为解决问题。
And any problem in the world, be it CS or otherwise, has some input.
世界上任何问题，无论是计算机科学还是其他领域，都有输入。
And we decided how to represent those inputs.
我们决定如何表示这些输入。
It needs some output, the solution there, too.
它需要输出，也就是解决方案。
And then all of what you focused on doing and learning and applying these past several weeks is in that proverbial black box, which hopefully is not such an abstraction anymore, but is indeed something that you know how to harness.
过去几周你所专注于做、学习和应用的一切都在那个众所周知的“黑匣子”里，希望它对你来说不再那么抽象，而是你确实知道如何利用的东西。
know what could be going on underneath the hood, even if it's in some technology or some language that maybe we ourselves didn't cover because a lot of those first principles remain the same.
你知道底层是如何运作的，即使它使用的是我们可能没有涵盖的技术或语言，因为很多基本原理都是相同的。
Now, along the way, we talked about the quality of solutions to those problems.
在此过程中，我们讨论了这些问题的解决方案的质量。
We happened to focus on correctness, just does it work, design, which is a bit more qualitative and subjective, and then style, the aesthetics of it all.
我们碰巧关注的是正确性，也就是它是否有效，设计，这更定性和主观一些，以及风格，也就是整体的美观程度。
And these, too, are characteristic, maybe not with these same words, of just how you might write or evaluate other creations in life, be it physical or written or the like.
这些也是你在生活中如何撰写或评估其他作品的特征，也许不是用同样的词语，无论是实体的、书面的还是其他形式的。
So think about, too, as you solve problems, just how you can sort of frame for yourself, like, am I doing a good job or not, by quantizing it along these or perhaps other axes as well.
思考一下，在你解决问题时，如何通过量化这些或者其他方面来判断自己是否做得很好。
And we thought we'd highlight just two topics from that week zero that have really been manifest for the past several weeks, namely abstraction, like taking complicated things and ideas and trying to simplify them so that
我们想强调零周以来的两个主题，它们在过去几周里反复出现，那就是抽象，比如把复杂的事物和想法简化，
we can sort of operate at this level and solve problems we care about without getting into the weeds of implementation detail, so to speak.
这样我们就可以在更高的层次上操作，解决我们关心的问题，而不用陷入具体的实现细节。
But there's this tension, because you know now from all of these different languages that code is fairly unforgiving.
但这其中存在一种矛盾，因为你现在从所有这些不同的语言中了解到，代码是相当不宽容的。
I mean, even omitting a stupid semicolon sometimes breaks everything.
我的意思是，即使漏掉一个分号，有时也会毁掉一切。
And so precision is sort of at odds sometimes with this idea of leveraging abstraction.
因此，精确性有时与利用抽象的概念相冲突。
And so we thought we would try to tease this apart, especially all these weeks later here, but with a bit of a live demonstration.
所以我们想尝试理清这一点，尤其是在几周后的今天，通过一个现场演示。
So on the way in, you probably all received a sheet of paper.
在进来的路上，你们可能都收到了一张纸。
If not, but someone near you did, just tear theirs in half and borrow half a sheet if you can, or any piece of loose-leaf paper or the like will suffice, so long as you have a pen or a pencil.
如果没有，但你旁边的人有，就把他们的撕成两半，借用半张，或者任何一张活页纸都可以，只要你有笔就行。
And for this, allow me to propose that we invite up maybe two final CS50 volunteers this semester.
为此，我提议我们邀请两位同学作为本学期最后两位 CS50 志愿者。
And a lot of hands are going up in this.
很多人都举手了。
OK, a lot of hands.
好的，很多只手。
How about I saw the first hand there.
我看到第一个举手的是那边那位。
Yes, yes, yes, who's pointing at herself now.
对，对，对，就是现在指着自己的那位。
Come on down.
请下来吧。
We just need the one hand for now.
我们现在只需要一位。
Oh, wait, you'll be our number two.
等等，你将是我们的第二位。
OK, we have way too many volunteers now.
我们现在有太多志愿者了。
No, no, please, please, come down.
不，不，请下来吧。
Yes, in the black shirt.
对，穿黑衣服的那位。
And if you guys, we will do pair programming in just a bit.
过一会儿，你们将进行结对编程。
If you want to hang out in the wings here, we'll have our second demonstration as well.
如果你想在这里稍等片刻，我们一会儿还有第二个演示。
So OK, now maybe a round of applause for our three volunteers.
现在，也许我们可以给三位志愿者一轮掌声。
Come on up first.
第一个，请上台。
Second and third.
第二个和第三个。
OK, you come first.
好，你先来。
This is a queue.
这是一个队列。
OK, queue.
好的，队列。
What's your name? Danny, OK, take this mic.
你叫什么名字？Danny，拿着这个麦克风。
OK, so we will DQ you momentarily.
我们马上会让你出列。
All right, so Danny, come on over to the middle here.
Danny，请到中间来。
And in a moment, I'm going to hand to Danny a sheet of paper that has a picture on it.
稍后，我会给 Danny 一张纸，上面有一张图片。
And this picture is going to be something that I'd like you to verbally program the audience to draw.
我希望你能用语言描述这幅图，让观众把它画出来。
You can use any words, any abstractions, any level of precision that you want.
你可以使用任何词语、任何抽象概念、任何你想要的精确度。
But you just can't make hand gestures or sort of show them what to draw.
但你不能用手势或其他方式向他们展示要画什么。
But first, you want to tell us a little something about yourself, including everyone here?
但首先，你想先向我们简单介绍一下你自己吗，包括在座的各位？
I'm Danny, and I took CS50.
我是 Danny，我上过 CS50。
OK, wonderful, wonderful.
太好了，太好了。
So I'm going to reveal the picture only to Danny.
我只向 Danny 展示图片。
And if each of you would like to take out that sheet of paper and just make sure that no one else can see this, if you want to hold it up this way.
如果你们每个人都想拿出那张纸，并确保没有人能看到它，你们可以这样举着它。
Everyone here is now holding their pen or pencil.
现在每个人都拿着你们的钢笔或铅笔。
And in some number of steps, give them a verbal algorithm for drawing what you see.
用一些步骤，口头描述一个算法，让别人能画出你看到的图形。
And you can say anything you want, but no hand gestures.
你可以说任何你想说的，但不能用手势。
OK, so you're going to want to draw a square in the center of the paper with the diagonal pointing to the left. center of the edge.
你要在纸的中心画一个正方形，对角线指向左边的中心。
Wait, no, actually, scratch that.
等等，不，实际上，划掉那个。
Draw a rhombus in the center of your paper.
在纸的中心画一个菱形。
And for those who forget what a rhombus is?
对于那些忘记菱形是什么的人？
For a diamond, a square that's on its side.
就是一个钻石的形状，一个侧放的正方形。
And then from the bottom vertex, draw a straight line down, but not all the way to the edge of the paper.
然后从底部的顶点，向下画一条直线，但不要一直画到纸的边缘。
Okay, and then keep your pencil or pen at that point and you're going to want to draw a line that's parallel to the line of the original rhombus to the right.
然后把你的铅笔或钢笔放在那个点上，你要画一条线，与原始菱形的右边平行。
And then keep your pencil or pen at that point and draw a line straight up connecting to the side vertex.
然后把你的铅笔或钢笔放在那个点上，向上画一条直线，连接到侧面的顶点。
Yes, and then go back to the line that you drew from the bottom vertex to the bottom of the paper and then draw a line parallel to the left edge of the rhombus.
是的，然后回到你从底部顶点到纸的底部画的那条线，然后画一条平行于菱形左边的线。
And then keep your pencil at that point and draw a line up to the vertex of the rhombus again.
然后把你的铅笔放在那个点上，向上画一条线，再次连接到菱形的顶点。
The end?
结束了吗？
All right.
好的。
Well, thank you to Danny.
谢谢 Danny。
Hang on to your paper.
拿着你的纸。
Thank you so much.
非常感谢你。
And if you want to step off to the stage there, we will reveal.
如果你想走下舞台，我们会揭晓答案。
Thank you.
谢谢。
A round of applause, if we could, for Danny.
我们为 Danny 鼓掌，如果可以的话。
That is not an easy task, I'm sure.
这可不是件容易的事，我相信。
And if Carter wouldn't mind just grabbing a few samples here, let's actually take a look on the overhead, if we could.
如果 Carter 不介意的话，请帮我拿几份样本。我们把它放在投影仪上看看。
I'm going to pop down over here real fast.
我马上就下来。
We don't need to collect them all, but if you're feeling either good or bad with what you drew, happy to collect a few of them.
我们不需要全部收集，如果你对自己画的感到满意或不满意，可以交上来几份。
OK.
好的。
Thank you.
谢谢。
OK.
好的。
Hope you won't mind if I can't reach everyone.
希望你们不会介意我没办法走到每个人身边。
Just a couple more.
再来几份。
OK.
好的。
Over here.
这边。
OK. All right.
可以了。
That's plenty.
足够了。
OK.
好的。
This one's really funny.
这个真有意思。
OK. I'm going to go with this one, if I may.
我选这个，如果可以的话。
And Carter has some, too.
Carter 也拿了一些。
OK, thank you so much.
非常感谢。
OK, so just a random assortment here.
只是一些随机的样本。
Let me turn on a camera so I can show you what I see.
我打开摄像头，这样就能让你们看到我所看到的。
Here, for instance, is one classmate's drawing, which might resemble perhaps what you drew here.
例如，这是一位同学的画，可能和你画的有点像。
Here is the beginnings of a house, it seems.
这看起来像是一栋房子的雏形。
Nice.
不错。
This one, OK, this one is larger.
这个，好吧，这个更大。
And how about a couple of others that we're getting closer, I think.
还有其他一些，我认为我们越来越接近了。
OK, so more edges and vertices there.
这里有更多的边和顶点。
This one seems a little similar in spirit, if not proportional.
这个看起来有点相似，即使比例不太对。
This is Zach's, the best one.
这是 Zach 的，画得最好。
But it turns out, if I may, Zach, you're not all that far off.
但事实证明，Zach，如果你不介意我说的话，你画的并没有差很多。
Here, Danny, is what you were reciting to everyone algorithmically.
Danny，这就是你用算法向大家描述的内容。
Indeed, it was this here cube.
没错，就是这个立方体。
And so Danny, can you come on back up for a moment?
Danny，你能再上来一下吗？
So if you'd like to share for just a moment, what were some of the thoughts going through your head, and why did you choose the words that you did?
你能简单分享一下你当时的想法吗？为什么选择那些词语？
OK.
好的。
So what was going through my head when I saw the cube?
我看到立方体的时候在想什么？
I didn't know if I could say, draw a cube.
我不知道能不能直接说“画一个立方体”。
So I decided to start with the top.
所以我决定从顶部开始。
And so draw a rhombus in the center of your paper.
在纸的中央画一个菱形。
And then draw a line down.
然后画一条线下来。
And just do the first part, then the second part, then the third part. And then you would get a cube, like Zach.
先画第一部分，然后是第二部分，然后是第三部分。 这样就能像 Zach 一样画出一个立方体。
Yeah, and so had you said, and you could have said, draw a cube, which would be more of an abstraction, even that's not necessarily sufficiently precise, right?
是的，如果你说，你本可以说，画一个立方体，这将是一个更抽象的概念，即使这样也不一定足够精确，对吧？
Because you don't necessarily know what the orientation of that cube is, the size of it, the positioning on the paper.
因为你不一定知道立方体的方向、大小以及在纸上的位置。
So you instead took a lower level approach, which is not unlike Scratch.
所以你采取了一种更低级的方法，这与 Scratch 没什么不同。
If you think about Scratch being able to move up, down, left, right, Turn 90 degrees, turn 15 degrees, and the like.
如果你想想 Scratch 能够向上、向下、向左、向右移动，旋转 90 度，旋转 15 度等等。
I mean, that is ultimately how a lot of graphical programs and games even might be implemented, by really focusing at the level you do.
我的意思是，这最终是许多图形程序甚至游戏实现的方式，通过真正关注你所做的级别。
But of course, there's this tension with us humans, whereby we prefer often to think at this level, but even that might not be sufficient.
但当然，这对我们人类来说是种矛盾，因为我们通常更喜欢在这个层面上思考，但即使这样也可能不够。
Which is to say, here in week 10, these are still going to be and are hard problems.
也就是说，在第 10 周，这些问题仍然是并且是难题。
But a hand, if we could, one more time for Danny for getting us that far along.
但是，如果可以的话，让我们再次为 Danny 鼓掌，感谢他让我们走了这么远。
Thank you so much.
非常感谢你。
Let me give you a stress ball here.
给你一个减压球。
All right.
好的。
And if we could have both of our volunteers come up here.
我们能不能请两位志愿者都上来？
We're going to have, yes, come on up.
我们要请，是的，请上来。
Come on up and let me have you guys introduce yourselves in the middle here.
请上来，请你们在中间做一下自我介绍。
Hi, I'm Evan. Hey there, I'm Serik from Turkey.
嗨，我是 Evan。大家好，我是来自土耳其的 Serik。
Nice to meet you all.
很高兴见到大家。
Wonderful.
太棒了。
Welcome.
欢迎。
And this time, we're going to flip it around so as to have the audience do what Danny just did for us.
这次，我们要反过来，让观众来做 Danny 刚才为我们做的事情。
The only catch here is that the only means we have for showing the audience what they need to tell you to draw is literally right above the chalkboard.
唯一的问题是，我们用来向观众展示他们需要告诉你画什么的方式，就是黑板正上方的内容。
So honor system here, that your eyes must stay on the chalkboard and not look up.
咱们说好了啊，你们只能看黑板，不能抬头。
And in just a moment, if you guys want to both stand in front of the chalkboard back to the audience,
等一下，你们二位可以走到黑板前，背对观众。
And as you're talking with each other, verbalize it through the microphone, if you will.
你们互相讨论的时候，记得用麦克风说话。
I'm going to show everyone else in the room a second and final drawing.
我要给大家看第二张也是最后一张图。
And we'll just go rapid fire around the room, give us one step at a time collectively.
然后我们快速过一遍，大家一步一步地说。
And we'll see if these guys can't draw exactly that same outcome.
看看他们能不能画出完全一样的结果。
So. Is there another chunk?
还有其他部分吗？
What's that?
什么？
Is there another chunk?
还有其他部分吗？
Just the one.
就这些。
So you'll have to collaborate.
你们要合作完成。
And let's give you a clean slate here, literally.
我们来擦干净，从字面上理解。
All right, so no looking up.
好了，不能抬头。
That's the only rule for you guys. Here we go.
这是对你们的唯一要求，开始了。
For the audience, here is what we'd like them, ironically, to draw.
为了让观众参与进来，我们想让他们，讽刺的是，画出我们想让他们画的东西。
Step one from anyone in the audience.
第一步，哪位观众来说？
Yes?
是的？
Draw a circle.
画个圆圈。
Anywhere.
任何地方都行。
Not anywhere.
不行，不是任何地方。
OK, that's step one.
第一步完成。
Step two, someone else.
第二步，其他人来。
Yeah, in the middle.
好的，中间。
Draw a line down from the bottom of the circle about halfway down.
从圆圈底部向下画一条线，大约到一半的位置。
I think there was a hand in front of you, too.
我觉得你前面也有一只手。
Number three?
第三步？
OK.
好的。
The overarching goal here for those unable to hear is to draw a person.
对于那些听不见的人来说，我们的总体目标是画一个人。
OK.
好的。
It may be a sick figure.
这可能是一个病人形象。
Draw the left leg of the person, of this person.
画出这个人的左腿。
OK.
好的。
Good job.
做得好。
All right.
好的。
Next, step four.
接下来，第四步。
Yeah. OK.
好的。
To the right of the vertex at the bottom of the circle, draw a V. Nope, not interactive.
在圆圈底部顶点的右侧，画一个 V。不，不是互动环节。
Draw a V. Get ready for step five.
画一个 V。准备第五步。
OK, we'll go with that. Step five, someone else.
就这样吧。第五步，其他人来。
Someone else, yeah.
其他人，对。
Draw the right side of the leg.
画腿的右边。
Nice.
棒极了。
Step six.
第六步。
Six.
六。
Yes.
是的。
Erase the line that you have on the left.
擦掉左边的那条线。
OK.
好的。
Step seven. Yes.
第七步，对。
Instead of that line before going up, make it go down.
之前向上画的线，现在向下画。
OK, step eight.
好，第八步。
Step eight.
第八步。
Yes?
是吗？
Connect that line to the hip.
把那条线连到臀部。
Not touching.
不要碰到。
Something like this, maybe.
也许像这样。
OK, compromise.
好，折中一下。
Not touching.
不要碰到。
OK.
好的。
Not touching.
不要碰到。
OK. All right.
好的。
Step nine.
第九步。
Almost there, I think.
快完成了。
Step nine.
第九步。
Step 9.
Yes, in back.
对，在后面。
Write the word high on the top left of the circle.
在圆圈的左上方写下 high。
OK.
好的。
And step 10.
第十步。
Almost there.
快完成了。
Draw a line pointing to high.
画一条指向 high 的线。
OK. And step 10, 11. Yeah.
好的，第十、十一步，对。
Erase the exclamation point.
擦掉感叹号。
Nice.
漂亮。
12.
第十二步。
Do we want to give them one more?
我们还要再给他们一步吗？
12, or are we good?
第十二步，还是这样就可以了？
Yeah, last one.
对，最后一步。
Erase the right arm.
擦掉右臂。
OK, I think we're going to need a 13 then.
那我们还需要第十三步。
And then?
然后呢？
Yeah.
对。
Repeat the left arm, but rotate it by 90 degrees.
重复左臂，但将其旋转 90 度。
That feels wrong.
这感觉不对。
As an organic human being, how would you put your arms?
作为一个有机的人类，你会怎么放你的胳膊？
Would you ever stretch your arm like that?
你会把手臂伸展成那样吗？
That would not be a stick figure.
那就不像火柴人了。
Would you do this, or would you do that?
你会这样做，还是那样做？
A little hint, maybe?
给点提示，也许？
Give me a step 14. Step 14 and final. Step 14?
告诉我第 14 步。第 14 步，也是最后一步。第 14 步？
I think we just got to tell them what to do. Step 14.
我觉得我们只需要告诉他们该怎么做。第 14 步。
Yes.
对。
Think of a walking man and have the right hand walking to your right.
想象一个行走的人，右手朝你的右边行走。
Where could the hand go?
手可以放在哪里？
Where should the hand go on that arm?
手应该放在那只胳膊的什么地方？
But yeah, yeah, OK, yes, no.
对，对，好的，是的，不。
Yeah, I mean, look right here.
对，我的意思是，看这里。
Look right here.
看这里。
Yes, all right, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
14 seconds.
14 秒。
That's pretty close.
非常接近了。
So congratulations to you guys, and thank you as well.
恭喜各位，也谢谢大家。
All right.
好的。
So I mean, these things too are not, yes, a round of applause then, sure.
我的意思是，这些事情也不需要掌声，当然。
So this is to say that these ideas of abstraction and precision and really every other term of art that we explored this term are sort of omnipresent and can be easier or harder to implement depending on exactly what the problem is.
也就是说，抽象、精确以及我们这学期探讨的每一个其他艺术术语，其实都无处不在，而且根据具体问题的不同，实现起来可能更容易，也可能更难。
But what we thought we'd do now in our final day is try to now similarly prepare you for life after CS50.
在我们今天的最后一课上，我们想做的是，同样尝试帮助大家为 CS50 之后的学习和生活做好准备。
And this is really going to be a list of, Really, potential to-dos, so that you can stand on your own after the class, after the class's infrastructure, write actual code.
这实际上是一个待办事项清单，让大家在完成这门课和课程基础架构学习之后，能够独立编写实际代码。
And then we'll come full circle one final time with our friend Jennifer Eightley to look at the world of emojis and how they relate to all forms of representation that we've talked about up until now.
我们将和我们的朋友 Jennifer Eightley 一起，最后一次回顾 Emoji 的世界，以及它们与我们到目前为止讨论过的所有表现形式之间的关系。
So one, how can you go about programming after CS50?
那么，在 CS50 之后，如何进行编程呢？
So one, you can actually install command line tools on your own Mac or PC.
首先，你可以在自己的 Mac 或 PC 上安装命令行工具。
Perhaps unbeknownst to you, Windows has what's generally called a command prompt.
你可能不知道，Windows 也有一个通常被称为命令提示符的工具。
Mac OS literally comes with a terminal program in your Applications Utilities folder.
Mac OS 在“应用程序”文件夹的“实用工具”文件夹中自带一个终端程序。
And so even if you've never run those programs, you've actually had a sort of blinking cursor, black and white prompt available to you.
因此，即使你从未运行过这些程序，你实际上也已经拥有了一个闪烁的光标，一个黑白相间的命令行界面。
Might not have all of the same software installed as your code space in the cloud, but you have that command line interface even within today's graphical tools.
它可能没有像你在云端的代码空间那样安装了所有相同的软件，但即使在今天的图形化工具中，你也可以使用命令行界面。
And among the tools you can install, Within that command line interface would be something called Xcode on the Mac, which comes not only with a GUI, IDE, Integrated Development Environment, but also those command line tools.
你可以在命令行界面中安装的工具之一是 Mac 上的 Xcode，它不仅带有 GUI、IDE（集成开发环境），还带有命令行工具。
And Microsoft, for Windows, has something similar as well. Learning Git.
Microsoft 也为 Windows 提供了类似的工具。 学习 Git。
So we've used Git only unbeknownst to you underneath the hood, for the most part.
在大多数情况下，我们在 CS50 课程中一直在后台使用 Git，你可能没有意识到。
But Git is a very, very, Popular tool, if challenging to pick up for the first time, that makes it easy to push code to a website called GitHub, or any equivalent, and then collaborate more effectively with classmates.
但 Git 是一个非常流行的工具，虽然第一次上手很有挑战性，但它可以轻松地将代码推送到 GitHub 或任何类似的网站，从而更有效地与同学协作。
There's definitely a bit of a learning curve, but thanks to CS50's own Brian Yu, you can start, for instance, with a video like this.
这肯定需要一定的学习曲线，但多亏了 CS50 的 Brian Yu，你可以从观看这样的视频开始学习。
And this, indeed, is going to be one of these de facto standards in the real world, at least for the next several years, that you'll probably encounter if you work in tech, or really any company where you're doing some programming.
这确实是未来几年你在现实世界中会遇到的事实标准之一，
至少在未来几年是这样，如果你从事技术工作，或者任何需要编程的公司，你都可能会遇到这种情况。
VS Code itself will walk you through this process in the coming days. But you can indeed install it on your own Mac or PC.
在接下来的几天里，VS Code 会引导你完成这个过程。当然，你也可以在你自己的 Mac 或 PC 上安装它。
And what can you do when you write code?
当你写代码的时候，你能做什么？
Well, you can certainly write software for your Mac, for your PC, for your phone.
当然可以为你的 Mac、PC 或手机编写软件。
Or of course, per week 9, you can host your own website, be it static, as in week 8.
或者，根据第九周的内容，你可以托管自己的网站，可以是像第八周那样的静态网站。
Hosting it at websites like these, which generally have free or student-friendly accounts via which you can put something statically on the web in a real domain name that you might choose.
将网站托管在像这样的网站上，这些网站通常提供免费或对学生友好的账户，你可以通过这些账户将静态内容放在你选择的真实域名下。
Or you can host a full-fledged web app. And using student tiers on Amazon and Microsoft and Google's Cloud Services or others, you can sign up for, being a student certainly, a whole lot of free software, free hosting, so as to, if nothing else,
或者你可以托管一个完整的网络应用程序。利用亚马逊、
微软和谷歌云服务或其他公司的学生套餐，作为学生，你当然可以注册大量的免费软件和免费托管服务，这样一来，至少可以
Experiment and perhaps maximally get your own app or website up and running.
进行实验，并且最大限度地让自己的应用程序或网站运行起来。
So know that those are resources available to you.
要知道，这些资源都是为你准备的。
And this is by certainly a non-exhaustive list.
当然，这并不是一个详尽的清单。
If you'd like to geek out in the coming months, in the coming years, these are just some of the places that people who take computer science classes, who write code, might tend to hang out and ask and answer questions of each other.
如果你想在未来的几个月甚至几年里成为极客，这些只是一些学习计算机科学课程和编写代码的人经常光顾、互相提问和解答问题的地方。
So keep an eye, for instance, on these here.
请密切关注这里。
And then CS50 has its own communities, as you'll see.
然后 CS50 有自己的社区，你会看到的。
If you go to this URL here via the OpenCourseWare version of CS50, which is open to the world, is there a vibrant community, thanks to time zones,
如果你通过 CS50 的 OpenCourseWare 版本访问这个 URL，它对全世界开放，你会发现那里有一个充满活力的社区，
talking about not only CS50 goings-on and problem that's pretty much active 24-7, 365, sets and projects, but really technology more generally as well.
由于时区的不同，这个社区几乎全天候活跃，讨论的不仅是 CS50 的进展、习题集和项目，还有更广泛的技术。
So certainly feel welcome to partake, either asking or answering questions.
欢迎你参与进来，无论是提问还是回答问题。
Now, speaking of asking and answering questions, a couple of weeks ago, you kindly gave us a whole bunch of review questions, which we called through and picked out our favorite 20 of them.
说到提问和回答问题，几周前，你们好心地给了我们一大堆复习题，我们从中挑选了最喜欢的 20 道题。
These, of course, were multiple choice questions.
当然，这些都是选择题。
And in preparation for this week, in preparation for life ahead, we thought we would choreograph a bit of a quiz show here.
为了准备这周的内容，也为了未来的生活，我们想在这里编排一场小测验。
And indeed, as you came in at the start of class,
事实上，当你在上课开始时进来的时候，
You might recall being invited to go to this URL here, cs50.ly, either here in person or if you're watching live from home, at this URL here.
你可能还记得被邀请访问这个 URL，cs50.ly，无论你是在现场还是在家观看直播，都可以访问这个 URL。
You can use a phone or a laptop.
你可以用手机或笔记本电脑。
And if it's easier on a phone, you can point your camera at this 2D barcode here.
如果用手机更方便，你可以将摄像头对准这里的二维条码。
We'll give folks a moment to pull that up.
我们会给大家一点时间打开它。
And again, that URL was cs50.ly slash pull.
再说一遍，网址是 cs50.ly/pull。
And Once it looks like most folks have it up and running, our friend Carter here will help us dive into this review session, if you will, with a bit of fun along the way.
当大多数人都打开并运行后，我们的朋友 Carter 将带我们一起回顾，一路上还会有一些乐趣。
All right, Carter, if you'd like to take it away.
Carter，你可以开始了。
What do we have as our first question?
我们的第一个问题是什么？
You should see on your phone or laptop this same question being asked.
你会在手机或笔记本电脑上看到同样的问题。
The first question is, how do you print, quote unquote, hello world in Python?
第一个问题是如何用 Python 打印“hello world”？
So among the possible answers are these here.
这些是可能的答案。
Buzz in on your phone or your laptop.
用你的手机或笔记本电脑选择答案。
We've got a few hundred responses already.
我们已经收到了几百个回复。
Seven seconds to make your decision.
还有 7 秒钟做决定。
This is question one of 20.
这是 20 个问题中的第一个。
Go into it with some confidence.
要有点信心。
I think we're down to zero on the clock.
时间到。
And Carter, it looks like 98% of you indeed said hello world.
Carter，看起来你们 98% 的人都选择了 `hello world`。
And Carter, per the check mark, that's indeed the correct answer here.
Carter，根据对勾，这确实是正确答案。
Now, to make things interesting, know that you'll see some number of points.
为了增加趣味性，你会看到一些分数。
And we've deliberately anonymized it so only you know what number you are.
我们特意进行了匿名处理，所以只有你自己知道你的分数。
So a whole lot of guests have a perfect score of 1,000 at the moment.
现在有很多选手的得分都是满分 1000 分。
Hopefully, we'll see over the next several questions things start to bridge out.
希望在接下来的几道题中，我们能看到分数开始出现差距。
But know that the speed with which you buzz in will also factor into how many points you now get.
但要知道，你抢答的速度也会影响你得到多少分。
So the faster you move, the more points you get.
所以你反应越快，得到的分数就越多。
Question two, if we could.
请看第二题。
What does DNS stand for?
DNS 代表什么？
From just a couple of weeks back, Domain Number System, Domain Name System, Data Numbering Structure. There's no such thing as DNS.
选项有：Domain Number System、Domain Name System、Data Numbering Structure、 There's no such thing as DNS！
A few hundred responses are in.
已经有几百个答案了。
Eight seconds remain.
还剩 8 秒。
Fewer points now, but still a chance to buzz in.
现在分数少了，但你还有机会抢答。
And now, as we hit zero, the responses are these.
时间到，大家的答案是：
Domain name system, which is indeed correct.
Domain Name System，完全正确。
And 84% of you got that one correctly.
84% 的人都答对了这道题。
And indeed exists.
它的确存在。
We talked about it a couple of weeks ago.
我们几周前讲过。
So we're still seeing a whole lot of ties at 2,000.
现在还有很多人都是 2000 分。
We'll see if someone starts to pull away before long.
我们看看是否有人会很快领先。
Question three.
第三题。
What is the upper bound of merge sorts runtime?
归并排序运行时间的上限是多少？
So that escalated quickly.
这升级得很快啊。
Big O of n log n, big O of log n, omega of log n, or big O of 1.
大 O(n log (n))，大 O(log (n))，Ω(log (n))，还是大 O(1)？
What is the upper bound of merge sorts runtime?
归并排序运行时间的上限是什么？
That was the last of the algorithms we saw for sorting.
这是我们看到的最后一个排序算法。
And in one second, we'll see that the correct answer is just edging out everyone else.
一秒钟后，我们会看到正确答案略微领先于其他答案。
Indeed, 46%.
确实是 46%。
It is n. I know.
是 n。我知道。
It's n log n.
是 n log (n)。
Now, if I may, as the teacher, it can't be log n, because log n is strictly less than n. And you can't possibly sort n elements unless you minimally look at or touch each of them.
如果我可以说，作为老师，它不可能是 log n，因为 log n 严格小于 n。你不可能对 n 个元素进行排序，除非你至少查看或触摸了其中每一个元素。
So it's got to be at least greater than n intuitively.
所以直观地说，它至少要大于 n。
We still have a whole bunch of ties.
我们还有很多平局。
Let's move on to number four.
我们来看第四题。
What is stored in argc?
argc 中存储了什么？
Back to the language C. Is it an array of arguments, the maximum size of an array, the count of arguments given to a program when first run, or how much memory is allocated to a function?
回到 C 语言。它是参数数组、数组的最大大小、程序首次运行时传递给程序的参数计数，还是分配给函数的内存大小？
Again, you wrote all of these questions.
再说一遍，这些问题都是你们写的。
And we have five seconds for the reveal.
我们有五秒钟的时间来揭晓答案。
argc is?
argc 是？
Indeed, the count of arguments given to a program when first run.
确实是程序首次运行时传递给它的参数计数。
Think back to C. When we did command line arguments, there was argc and argv.
回想一下 C 语言。当我们使用命令行参数时，有 argc 和 argv。
Argv was the array, but argc was indeed the count, the C in argc.
argv 是数组，但 argc 确实是计数，argc 中的 C。
All right, we still have a whole bunch of ties at the top here.
现在仍然有很多选手并列第一。
But let's move on then to number five.
让我们来看第五题。
What is the Duck Debugger's favorite hobby, according to one of your classmates?
根据一位同学的说法，Duck Debugger 最喜欢的爱好是什么？
dressing up like Dracula, swimming across the stage, filling up the entire bathroom of a guy's house, and sitting quietly on stage.
打扮成吸血鬼德古拉，游过舞台，把一个男人家的浴室填满，静静地坐在舞台上。
The third, of course, is a reference to a YouTube video that was on the course's website that week.
第三个选项，当然是引用了那周课程网站上的一个 YouTube 视频。
But according to your classmates, number two, seconds remaining sitting quietly on stage is its favorite pastime.
但根据同学们的回答，第二个选项，还剩几秒，静静地坐在舞台上是它最喜欢的消遣。
So a little harder, perhaps, than the others.
所以这道题可能比其他的要难一些。
5,000, now we're starting to see some spread.
5000 分，现在我们开始看到一些差距了。
So we only have six guests in contention for first place.
现在只有六位选手有希望争夺第一名。
And the next question now is six, what is the function used to open a file in C?
下一个问题是第六题，在 C 语言中，用于打开文件的函数是什么？
F open, open, file open, file.
fopen、open、fileopen、file。
What is the function used to open a file in C?
在 C 语言中，用于打开文件的函数是什么？
Seven seconds.
7 秒。
There's some differences between C and Python here.
C 语言和 Python 在这里有一些区别。
And the reveal, it is indeed fopen.
答案揭晓，确实是 fopen。
It's 77% correct, too.
正确率为 77%。
All right, let's see the rankings now.
让我们看看现在的排名。
If you are guessed 15, 97, 15, 6, 1, 7, 1, 3, 7, 5, 3, or 3, 2, 7, 3, you're now in the lead as we move on to question 7.
如果你猜的是 15、97、15、6、1、7、1、3、7、5、3、3、2、7、3，那么在进入第 7 题时，你现在处于领先地位。
How does Sterling compute the average, sorry, how does Sterling compute the length of a string in C?
string 如何计算平均值，抱歉，string 如何计算 C 语言中字符串的长度？
It looks at how much memory the string uses.
它会查看字符串使用了多少内存。
It counts the number of characters until it reaches backslash 0.
它会计算字符数，直到遇到反斜杠 0。
It counts the number of bits in the string, or it creates pointers for each character and counts them.
它计算字符串中的位数，或者为每个字符创建指针并进行计数。
10 seconds.
10 秒。
Sterling in C.
用 C 语言实现的 string。
Recall that we implemented this ourselves in class, but then we used the library thereafter.
回想一下，我们之前在课堂上自己实现了它，但之后就使用了库函数。
And indeed, with 85%, it simply counts the number of characters until it reaches that sentinel, backslash 0, a.k.a.
实际上，85% 的情况下，它只是简单地计算字符数，直到遇到反斜杠 0，也就是
null.
空字符。
And in this case, we have 5, 4, 4 of you tied now for first.
在这种情况下，我们有 5、4、4 个人并列第一。
All right, question 8.
好了，问题 8。
Where does malloc allocate memory from?
`malloc` 从哪里分配内存？
The stack, the heap, the pointers, or the temp?
栈、堆、指针还是临时存储区？
Where does malloc allocate memory from?
`malloc` 从哪里分配内存？
Responses are coming in.
答案正在涌入。
Eight seconds.
8 秒。
Good review question at that.
这是一个很好的复习题。
In two seconds, we'll see that malloc allocates memory from close one.
两秒钟后，我们会看到 `malloc` 从接近一的答案中分配内存。
The heap is correct.
堆是正确的。
The stack recall is where functions store their local variables and their arguments.
回想一下，栈是函数存储局部变量和参数的地方。
And that just happens automatically.
这都是自动发生的。
The heap, represented in our pictures up top, is where malloc draws from.
在我们上面的图片中表示的堆，就是 `malloc` 获取内存的地方。
Now we have guest 15 has
15号选手
Made its way to the top here, but others can catch up if they don't buzz in fast enough.
现在排在第一，但如果其他选手回答够快，还是可以赶上的。
So number nine, how many people flew from 50-ville to New York on the day of the crime?
9号选手，在案发当天，有多少人从50镇飞往纽约？
16, 29, 8, or 3?
16、29、8 还是 3？
Anyone with a laptop perhaps has an advantage here?
有笔记本电脑的人是不是更有优势？
Five seconds.
5秒钟。
And the answers are, but the answer is 16.
答案是，答案是16。
Let's see if guest 15 got this.
看看15号选手答对了吗。
They did not.
没有。
Goodbye to guest 15 at the top.
排名第一的15号选手再见了。
All right, question 10.
好的，第10题。
We're about halfway there.
我们已经进行到一半了。
What are meta tags used for in HTML?
在HTML中，<meta> 标签有什么用？
To describe a web page, to define parameters for an element, to group elements together, to translate content into machine-readable format.
描述网页、定义元素的参数、将元素分组、将内容转换为机器可读格式。
What are meta tags used for in HTML?
在HTML中，<meta> 标签有什么用？
We saw a few of them for different use cases.
我们已经见过几个不同用例的例子了。
And with one second, we see that, indeed, the number one answer was to describe the web page, be it for a mobile device, be it for screen scrapers like Facebook and Twitter and other such apps that grab images and descriptions thereof.
还剩一秒钟，我们可以看到，第一名的答案确实是描述网页，
无论是针对移动设备，还是针对像Facebook、Twitter以及其他抓取图像和描述的应用程序。
All right, we're in the second half now.
我们现在进入下半场。
Guest 4669 has edged ahead.
4669号选手领先了。
Guest 15 is now in sixth place.
15号选手现在排在第六位。
All right, number 11 is, how do you find the address of a variable in C?
好，第 11 题，如何在 C 语言中找到一个变量的地址？
Think back a few weeks, star, dollar sign, ampersand, or ask.
回想几周前的内容，星号，美元符号，&符号，还是询问？
From one of your own classmates, how do you find the address of a variable in C?
来自你的一位同学，如何在 C 语言中找到变量的地址？
And the number one answer is ampersand, which is indeed the address of operator at 62%.
排名第一的答案是&符号，也就是地址运算符，占比 62%。
Nicely done.
做得好。
Let's see who's atop the list now.
让我们看看现在谁排在榜首。
Guess 4, 6, 6, 9 has retained their lead.
4、6、6、9 号嘉宾仍然保持领先。
So we move on to 12.
我们继续第 12 题。
What does the arrow operator mean in C?
C 语言中的箭头运算符是什么意思？
A hyphen and a greater than sign.
一个连字符和一个大于号。
Nothing starts a comment, replaces a star and dot operator, declares a pointer.
不代表任何内容，替换星号和点运算符，声明一个指针。
What does this arrow operator mean in C?
这个箭头运算符在 C 语言中是什么意思？
Again, from a few weeks back.
同样是几周前的知识。
Three seconds.
3 秒钟。
Carter assortment, perhaps.
可能是各种各样的答案。
And it's, oh, replaces a star and dot operator.
答案是，替换星号和点运算符。
The number two answer was indeed correct.
第二个答案确实是正确的。
This was just a cleaner way, syntactic sugar, for collapsing what would be a star and then some parentheses and then a dot into quite simply something that looks like an arrow itself.
这是一种更简洁的写法，语法糖，将星号、括号和点号简化为一个看起来像箭头的符号。
All right, Carter, who's in the lead now?
卡特，现在谁领先？
Still that same guest.
还是那位嘉宾。
And let's see what 13 has for us.
让我们看看第13个问题是什么。
Which of these is not a data type in SQLite?
以下哪项不是 SQLite 中的数据类型？
Blob, string, integer, text.
Blob，string，integer，text。
We used a few of these more commonly than others, but not all of these are for real.
我们比较常用其中一些，但并非所有这些都是真实存在的。
Five seconds to make your decision.
你有五秒钟的时间做出决定。
And the results are blob is a thing, string is not in SQLite.
结果是：blob 是存在的，而 string 在 SQLite 中不存在。
It's, of course, called text, as we've seen it.
就像我们看到的那样，它被称为 text。
Blob, as goofy as it sounds, is just binary large object.
Blob，听起来很傻，其实就是二进制大对象。
But indeed, it's how you might store a binary file in your database.
但实际上，它是你可以在数据库中存储二进制文件的方式。
All right.
好的。
The rankings now, oh, guest 8444 has eked ahead.
现在的排名，嘉宾 8444 领先了。
So we move on to 14.
我们继续第 14 个问题。
Which of the following is a valid way to print exclamation point, exclamation point, exclamation point, exclamation point in Python?
以下哪种方法可以在 Python 中打印四个感叹号？
I'll let you read these yourselves, which is a valid way.
我让你们自己阅读，哪种方法是有效的。
Everyone got quiet in his thinking.
每个人都在静静地思考。
All right, six seconds.
好的，六秒钟。
A few hundred responses in so far.
目前为止有几百个回复。
All right, and yes, nicely done. 78% is correct.
做得好。78% 的人答对了。
You can use the star operator to essentially multiply the character at left.
你可以使用星号运算符来“乘以”左边的字符。
All right, who's in the lead, Carter?
谁领先了，Carter？
We now have still guest 8444, and so we move on now to 15.
嘉宾 8444 仍然领先，我们继续第 15 题。
What does the free function do?
free 函数的作用是什么？
Deallocates memory from a primitive, deallocates memory at the given pointer, terminates a loop, or returns a value from the function.
从基本类型中释放内存、释放给定指针处的内存、终止循环或从函数返回一个值。
What does the free function do?
free 函数的作用是什么？
All right, five seconds.
好的，5 秒钟。
Does the free function do?
free 函数的作用是什么？
Calls the opposite, essentially, of malloc.
本质上是调用 malloc 的反向操作。
And it deallocates the memory at the given pointer as well.
它也释放给定指针处的内存。
And in C, that's on you.
在 C 语言中，这取决于你。
In Python, you don't need to worry about allocating or freeing a life.
在 Python 中，你不需要担心分配或释放内存。
All right.
好的。
We now have at the top, still guest 8444, and seeing more and more spread, 16, which is not a step of compiling.
现在排在最前面的是，嘉宾 8444，并且差距越来越大，第 16 题，哪个不是编译的步骤。
Think back now to week two, compiling, preprocessing, linking, or threading, which is not a step of compiling.
回想一下第二周的内容，编译、预处理、链接还是线程，哪个不是编译的步骤。
We use it as a catch-all, but it technically means a few different things collectively.
我们把它作为一个总称，但它在技术上指的是一些不同的东西的集合。
All right, and threading is indeed not on the list.
线程确实不在列表中。
That is a technical thing, generally meaning a program can do multiple things at once.
这是一个技术性的东西，通常意味着一个程序可以同时做多件事情。
But that is not related here to compiling.
但这与这里的编译无关。
All right, guest 8444 is still at the top.
嘉宾 8444 仍然位居榜首。
We have just a few questions left. And so 17.
我们只剩下几个问题了。所以第 17 题。
What was the surprise at the beginning of the Halloween lecture, according to your classmates?
根据同学们的描述，万圣节讲座开始时的惊喜是什么？
Someone scared me.
有人吓到我了。
Someone hid candy under every chair.
有人在每个椅子下面都藏了糖果。
Someone dressed up as me.
有人打扮成了我。
The entire staff dressed up as Carter.
全体员工都打扮成了 Carter。
Interesting litmus test of who came to or watched lecture, perhaps.
这可能是一个有趣的试金石，可以看出谁来听课或观看了课程。
Let's see which guests got this correct.
让我们看看哪些嘉宾答对了这道题。
Someone, someone's really dressed up as, indeed, me at 64%.
有人，确实有人打扮成了我，获得了 64% 的投票。
So I think we have attendance here, essentially, from that lecture.
所以我认为从那次讲座来看，大家基本上都来了。
So let's move on now to the final few questions after seeing that guest 8444 is still doing well.
现在让我们继续看最后几个问题，8444 号嘉宾仍然表现出色。
Can anyone dethrone them?
有人能取代他们吗？
Why is it incorrect to use the equals equals operator in C to compare strings?
为什么在 C 语言中使用等于等于运算符比较字符串是不正确的？
It's computationally inefficient.
计算效率低。
You're comparing the locations of the strings.
你在比较字符串的位置。
Strings don't exist.
字符串不存在。
Using equal equals will lead to buffer overflow.
使用等于等于会导致缓冲区溢出。
Why is it incorrect to use equal equals in C to compare strings?
为什么在 C 语言中使用等于等于来比较字符串是不正确的？
Three seconds.
3 秒钟。
We saw this live, and it motivated like an entire week because you're comparing the locations, that is, the addresses in memory of those same strings.
我们现场看到了这一点，这也促使我们进行了整整一周的学习，因为你比较的是位置，也就是内存中相同字符串的地址。
All right, let's see if this leaves the rankings the same.
好了，让我们看看这是否会让排名保持不变。
Guest 8444 is still at the top and pulling ahead.
8444 号嘉宾仍然位居榜首，并且遥遥领先。
Two final questions.
最后两个问题。
19, what is the difference between null, one L, and null, two Ls?
第19题，null（一个L）和null（两个L）之间有什么区别？
Null and null mean the same thing.
Null和null的意思相同。
Null refers to backslash 0, whereas null 2L's is the 0 address.
Null指的是反斜杠0，而有两个L的null指的是地址0。
Null is the 0 address, whereas null 2L's refers to backslash 0.
Null是地址0，而有两个L的null指的是反斜杠0。
Null is null, but lazier.
Null就是null，只是更懒惰的说法。
Five seconds.
5秒钟。
Subtle, not the best design, perhaps, to have in technical terms.
可能有点微妙，从技术角度来说，这不是最好的设计。
But indeed, 62% of you got that N-U-L is the first thing we talked about when we talked about backslash 0.
但实际上，你们中62%的人答对了，N-U-L是我们谈到反斜杠0时首先提到的。
And N-U-L-L is a pointer.
而N-U-L-L是一个指针。
It's the 0 pointer.
它是0指针。
Same number, but different context.
相同的数字，但上下文不同。
All right, Carter, guest 8444 is the person to beat with our final 20th questions.
Carter，8444号嘉宾以最后一个问题领先。
What do the binary bulbs on stage spell today?
今天舞台上的二进制灯泡拼出了什么？
And these are your four choices.
这是你们的四个选项。
Different from usual, we usually use 8-bit ASCII.
与往常不同，我们通常使用8位ASCII码。
Today, we are using UTF-8, which is a form of Unicode, which is the larger subset that uses 1 or 2 or 3 or even 4 bytes to spell a single character.
今天，我们使用UTF-8，它是Unicode的一种形式，Unicode是一个更大的字符集，它使用1、2、3甚至4个字节来表示一个字符。
And the answer, wow, close, is indeed a cupcake.
答案是，哇，很接近了，确实是纸杯蛋糕。
Indeed a cupcake.
确实是纸杯蛋糕。
Well done.
干得好。
And let's see the final results.
让我们看看最终结果。
8444 is the winner.
8444 是赢家。
Are they here in person, perhaps?
他们本人在这里吗？
8444? You're 8444?
8444？你是 8444？
Come on down.
请下来吧。
Thank you.
谢谢。
There you go.
给你。
Congratulations.
恭喜你。
All right.
好的。
So today, if we may, give me just one moment.
今天，如果可以的话，请给我一点时间。
All right.
好的。
All right, so today, we are so pleased to be joined by Jennifer A. Lee, who's an alumna of the college, a dear friend, and is actually really the reason why there's evidence of Muppets in CS50.
今天我们很高兴 Jennifer A. Lee 能加入我们，她是我们学院的校友，也是一位亲爱的朋友，实际上她是 CS50 中出现 Muppets 的原因。
In fact, some years ago, I was visiting her, and she had on her shelf this custom Muppet.
几年前我去拜访她，她架子上放着这个定制的 Muppet。
It wasn't one that appears on TV, but she had somehow gone on a website.
它没有出现在电视上，但她不知怎么地在一个网站上找到了它。
It's a former toy store called FAO Schwartz at the time.
当时那是一家名为 FAO Schwartz 的玩具店。
And you're allowed to configure your own Muppet whatnot. Choose the eyes, the nose, the face, and the torso.
你可以配置你自己的 Muppet，选择眼睛、鼻子、脸和躯干。
And I just thought this was the coolest thing.
我觉得这太酷了。
And so in the taxi on the way home, I was going on the website trying to purchase our very first Muppet.
所以在回家的出租车上，我打开了那个网站，想买我们第一个 Muppet。
I then woke up the next morning thinking, why did I just buy a puppet in the back of a taxi?
第二天早上醒来，我想，我为什么要在出租车后面买一个玩偶？
And so it sat on the shelf for really two years.
它在架子上放了两年。
And then a colleague of mine within CS50's team decided, after I brought it into the office to sit on a shelf there, to actually bring it to life.
然后我的一位 CS50 团队的同事在我把它带到办公室的架子上之后，决定把它真正地做出来。
And indeed, if you Google around CS50 Muppetry and Puppetry online, you'll see, in fact, these as characters not only over the past couple of years in COVID times, when really there was next to no one actually here.
事实上，如果你在网上搜索 CS50 Muppetry 和 Puppetry，
你会发现，在过去几年 COVID 期间，当这里几乎没有人时，这些角色不仅存在于网上。
And so they were instead.
而是它们代替了真人。
But indeed, she's brought not only this educational element, this pedagogical element, this playful element to CS50.
但她不仅为 CS50 带来了这种教育元素、教学元素，还带来了这种 playful 元素。
And we have her here today.
今天她来到了现场。
to speak to exactly the sorts of encodings that are here on stage.
来给大家讲解舞台上的编码。
Jenny is the former vice chair of the Unicode Subcommittee on Emoji, which is to say that she and her colleagues have been influential in taking emoji from what was a very limited character set early on
Jenny 是 Unicode Emoji 小组委员会的前副主席，也就是说，她和她的同事们对 Emoji 的发展起到了重要作用，
and by far unrepresentative of much human emotion and speech into really an initiative now to capture digitally all of the world's languages, past, present, and future.
将 Emoji 从早期非常有限的字符集，远远不能代表人类情感和语言，发展到现在真正成为一项捕捉世界上所有语言（过去、现在和未来）的倡议。
As well as the range of emotions that we might see here in the form of that pillow or even in the cake that awaits.
以及我们可能在这里看到的各种情绪，比如那个枕头，甚至是等待着的蛋糕。
So allow me to introduce Jennifer Eight Lee.
请允许我介绍 Jennifer Eight Lee。
Thank you.
谢谢。
I much drink.
我要喝点东西。
OK.
好的。
Clicker.
遥控器。
I have to hide my drinks.
我得把饮料藏起来。
I might need more water. All right.
我可能需要更多水。好的。
I'm really excited to speak here.
我很高兴能在这里演讲。
Last year I was here. One, I was wearing a mask, which is a real bummer if you're lecturing.
去年我也在这里。但是我戴着口罩，如果你要演讲的话，这真的很糟糕。
And the entire front part was all Muppets.
而且整个前面都是 Muppets。
So I'm really happy to see humans, actually.
所以我很高兴看到真人。
And it's always an honor to speak at Sanders.
在 Sanders 演讲是我的荣幸。
And then Dave and I were actually classmates way back when, so I do remember him when he was an undergrad, much like you.
我和 Dave 很久以前是同学，我记得他读本科的时候，很像你们现在这样。
So I'm going to give a talk on the world of emoji and how I kind of became an emoji activist.
我今天要讲的是 Emoji 的世界，以及我如何成为一名 Emoji 活动家。
So it kind of all starts with my friend Yiying Liu, who is a designer who is well known for doing the Twitter fail whale.
这一切都是从我的朋友 Yiying Liu 开始的，她是一位设计师，以设计 Twitter 失败鲸而闻名。
which was kind of laid to rest, except now this week it seems like it may be necessary again.
这个图案本来已经被搁置了，但似乎本周又要重新启用了。
So she and I one day were texting, this was back in 2015, we were texting about dumplings because we are Chinese-ish women and we like to text about food.
那是 2015 年，有一天我和她在发短信，我们都在聊饺子，因为我们是华人女性，都喜欢聊食物。
And so I sent her this picture of dumplings and she was like, yum, yum, yum, yum, yum, yum, yum, yum.
我给她发了这张饺子的照片，她说，好吃，好吃，好吃，好吃，好吃，好吃，好吃，好吃。
And then she was like, oh, Apple doesn't have a dumpling emoji.
然后她说， Apple 没有饺子 Emoji。
And I was like, oh, that's kind of interesting.
我说，这还挺有意思的。
I didn't really think anything about it, because people point things out to you all the time, and then you just forget.
我当时没想太多，因为人们总是会跟你指出各种事情，然后你就忘了。
You just move on.
继续做自己的事。
But then half an hour later, on my phone appears this dumpling with heart eyes.
但半小时后，我的手机上就出现了这个带着爱心的饺子。
And you don't see it because it's a still shot, but it actually had blinking eyes.
你们看不到，因为这是静态图片，但它实际上是眨着眼睛的。
So she liked to call it Bling Bling Dumpling.
所以她喜欢叫它“Bling Bling 饺子”。
So she, as a designer, had decided to go in and make her own dumpling emoji because she was like, I'm a designer, I can fix it.
作为一名设计师，她决定自己动手制作饺子 Emoji，因为她觉得，我是一名设计师，我可以搞定。
But that actually got me thinking. I was like, where do emoji come from? And how is there not a dumpling emoji. Because from my perspective, dumplings are this kind of universal food.
但这让我陷入了思考。我想，Emoji 是从哪里来的？为什么没有饺子 Emoji？因为在我看来，饺子是一种很普遍的食物。
Right. So and there are a lot of Japanese foods on the emoji keyboard. And I was not, this was like back in 2015.I was like not a big  emoji user like at all.
对吧。Emoji 键盘上有很多日本食物。当时是 2015 年，我根本不是一个 Emoji 的重度用户。
So I mean, you have things like ramen. You have Bento boxes. You have curry.You have tempura.
我们有拉面、便当盒、咖喱、天妇罗。
You even have kind of obscure kind of foods like this thing, things on a stick, turns out to be fish things on a stick. Then this pink and white swirly thing is also a fish thing.
甚至还有一些很奇怪的食物，比如这个东西，插在棍子上的东西，结果是插在棍子上的鱼。然后这个粉白相间的漩涡状的东西也是一种鱼。
And there's even like that triangle rice ball that looks like it's had a bikini wax, all well represented on the emoji keyboard, but no dumplings.
甚至还有那个看起来像做过比基尼脱毛的三角饭团，这些在 Emoji 键盘上都有，但就是没有饺子。
And it's very strange because all cultures kind of have their dumpling, whether or not it's ravioli or empanadas.
所有文化中都有一种类似饺子的食物，无论是意大利 ravioli 还是西班牙 empanadas。
Essentially everyone discovered the idea of yummy goodness inside a carbohydrate shell, whether or not baked or fried or steamed.
基本上所有人都发现了在碳水化合物外壳中包裹美味馅料的想法，无论是烤、炸还是蒸。
So, I was like, okay, I literally Googled, like, who controls emoji?
我当时就想，到底是谁控制着 Emoji？ 我真的用谷歌搜索了这个问题。
And you discover that they're actually regulated by a nonprofit called the Unicode Consortium.
然后我发现，它们实际上是由一个名为 Unicode 协会的非营利组织管理的。
And it is, you know, and I just, like, went on their website, and I discovered They were mostly U.S. multinational tech companies.
我打开了他们的网站，发现他们主要是美国的跨国科技公司。
Oracle, IBM, Microsoft, Adobe, Google, Apple, Facebook, and Yahoo.
Oracle、IBM、Microsoft、Adobe、Google、Apple、Facebook 和 Yahoo。
And of the three that were not multinational U.S.
在剩下的三家不是美国跨国公司的公司中。
tech companies, they were, let's see. German company called SAP, a Chinese telecom company called Huawei, and then the government of Oman.
让我想想，它们是一家名为 SAP 的德国公司，一家名为华为的中国电信公司，以及阿曼政府。
Those were basically the 12 poll-voting members of the U.S. multinational tech companies.
这基本上就是 Unicode 协会中拥有投票权的 12 个成员，都是美国跨国科技公司。
They at that point paid $18,000 a year to have full voting power on the Unicode committee.
当时，他们每年支付 18,000 美元，以获得 Unicode 委员会的全部投票权。
And I was like, oh, that's a lot of money.
我当时就想，这可真是一大笔钱。
And I kind of felt indignant about this.
我对此感到有点愤愤不平。
But then if you kind of keep on digging on their website, you found there was this kind of interesting loophole, which is you could join as an individual for $75.
但后来我继续浏览他们的网站，发现了一个有趣的漏洞：你可以以个人身份加入，只需 75 美元。
You don't get voting power, but it gave you the right to put yourself on the email list and also to attend the quarterly Unicode meeting.
虽然没有投票权，但你可以加入他们的邮件列表，还可以参加每季度的 Unicode 会议。
So I was like, I'll do that.
我当时就想，我可以试试。
I had no idea what I was doing. But I'm like, I'm going to go fight for this dumpling emoji.
虽然我不知道自己在做什么，但我心想，我要去为饺子 Emoji 而战。
Because from my perspective, dumplings are universal.
因为在我看来，饺子是全球通用的。
Emoji are kind of universal.
Emoji 也是全球通用的。
So the fact there was no dumpling emoji meant something was wrong in the universe, and I was determined to fix this.
没有饺子 Emoji 意味着宇宙中有什么地方出了问题，我决心要解决这个问题。
I was on this email list, and then a couple of, maybe even a couple of weeks later, they kind of send out this note that's like, hey, who's coming to the quarterly meeting?
我订阅了这个电子邮件列表，然后几周后，可能也就几周吧，他们发了一封邮件，说，嘿，谁来参加季度会议？
And I was like, I looked at the calendar, I looked at my schedule, I was like, oh, I'll be in like, Silicon Valley at that time.
我看了看日历，看了看我的行程安排，心想，那时候我应该在硅谷。
with very formal seats, people with gavels.
有着非常正式的座位，还有人拿着议事锤。
That is not what I found.
但我发现的并非如此。
Basically, it was a conference room full of people who skewed whiter, skewed older, skewed male, skewed engineers, and this is basically the room where it happened.
基本上就是一个会议室，里面坐满了人，而且这些人普遍更白、更老、男性更多、工程师更多，基本上就是在这个房间里决定的。
This is 2015. These were the people who decided your emoji.
那是在 2015 年。 这些人决定了你使用的 Emoji。
All very nice.
他们人都很好。
One even had a daughter who had a sense of humor and made him a shirt that said, shadowy emoji overlord.
其中一个人甚至有一个很有幽默感的女儿，她给他做了一件衬衫，上面写着“神秘的 Emoji 大魔王”。
So I just kind of listened to them debate things like milk emoji and beans emoji and it just seemed like not quite right to me that like it would be this global visual language that were basically decided by like a small group of people inside a conference room in Silicon Valley.
所以我只是听着他们讨论牛奶 Emoji 和豆子 Emoji 之类的东西，
在我看来，这种全球性的视觉语言由硅谷一间会议室里的一小群人来决定，这似乎不太对劲。
So I decided to form a group called Emoji Nation whose motto is like emoji by the people for the people and it basically advocates for more kind of representative inclusive
所以我决定成立一个名为 Emoji Nation 的小组，其座右铭是“人民的 Emoji 为人民服务”，它基本上是为了倡导更具代表性和包容性的 Emoji。
We started with a Kickstarter campaign, dumpling emoji process, trying to right the wrong in this world, and made this little cute video, sort of advocating.
我们从一个 Kickstarter 众筹活动开始，发起了饺子 Emoji 的进程，试图纠正这个世界上的错误，还制作了这个可爱的小视频来进行宣传。
Georgia has kinkali, Japan has gyoza, Korea has mandu, Italy has ravioli, Poland has pierogi, Russia has pelmeni, Argentina has empanadas, Jewish people have kreplech, China has potstickers, Nepal and Tibet have momos.
格鲁吉亚有 Khinkali，日本有饺子，韩国有 Mandu，意大利有 Ravioli，
波兰有 Pierogi，俄罗斯有 Pelmeni，阿根廷有 Empanadas，犹太人有 Kreplech，中国有锅贴，尼泊尔和西藏有 Momo。
Yet, somehow, despite their popularity, there is no dumpling emoji in the standard set.
然而，不知何故，尽管饺子很受欢迎，但在标准的 Emoji 集合中却没有它。
Why is that?
为什么会这样？
Emoji exists for pizza, tempura, sushi, spaghetti, hot dog, and now tacos, which Taco Bell takes credit for.
披萨、天妇罗、寿司、意大利面、热狗都有 Emoji，现在还有玉米卷，Taco Bell 声称这是他们的功劳。
We need to right this disparity.
我们需要纠正这种不平衡。
Dumplings are global.
饺子是全球性的。
Emoji are global.
Emoji 是全球性的。
Isn't it time we brought them together?
难道我们不应该把它们结合起来吗？
Oh yeah, and while we're at it, how about an emoji for Chinese takeout?
对了，既然说到了，为什么不来个中国菜外卖的表情符号呢？
So, I did put together a dumpling emoji proposal.
所以我确实提交了一个饺子的表情符号提案。
I wrote this, I remember Thanksgiving Day, 2015, on a plane, and we got it passed.
我记得很清楚，这是我2015年感恩节那天在飞机上写的，而且它通过了。
Basically, dumpling, takeout box, chopsticks, and fortune cookie.
基本上就是饺子、外卖盒、筷子和幸运饼干。
I have to say, I don't think Fortune Cookie would have made it on its own merits, but it kind of like slid in on the coattails of the other ones.
我必须得说，我认为幸运饼干本身可能不会被采纳，但它有点像沾了其他几个的光才得以通过。
And so these were the proposals as we submitted them.
所以这就是我们提交的提案。
And then these are the ones that kind of exist now on the Apple keyboard.
然后这些是现在出现在Apple键盘上的样子。
And I have to say the dumpling looks really, really realistic, oddly realistic.
我必须得说，饺子看起来真的非常逼真，出奇地逼真。
And whereas like the Fortune Cookie I think is like a big fail.
而幸运饼干我觉得就很失败。
Because first of all, there's like, it has no, it has no gap.
因为首先，它没有，它没有缝隙。
It looks like a dead 3D Pac-Man.
它看起来像一个死气沉沉的3D吃豆人。
So I'm very disappointed. in the manifestation of that.
所以我对它的最终呈现非常失望。
But that's okay.
不过没关系。
That's okay.
没关系。
And so it's kind of interesting, like, what is the process of getting an emoji passed?
所以这还挺有意思的，比如，让一个表情符号通过审核的流程是什么样的？
And I will sort of walk you through it.
我将大致向你们介绍一下。
So first of all, you come up with your idea, right?
首先，你要想出一个点子，对吧？
And then you kind of write this proposal, and then you submit it to the Unicode Emoji Subcommittee, who then kind of gives you comments and then sends it back to you, and you kind of go around and around in a circle.
然后你要写一份提案，然后提交给Unicode表情符号小组委员会，他们会给你反馈意见，然后发回给你，你就这样来回修改。
So these are things that we consider.So somewhere in there, I also fought my way onto the emoji committee and then also became a ViceChair, became a Vice Chair.
所以这些是我们会考虑的事情。在这期间的某个时候，我还努力加入了表情符号委员会，然后还成为了副主席。
Sort of an extracurricular just like completely run amok in my life.So things that matter popular demand,is it a frequently requested emoji.
这就像是我生活中一个完全失控的课外活动。重要的事情包括大众需求，它是否是一个经常被请求的表情符号。
Multiple usages and meanings.
多重用法和含义。
So that's actually kind of very important for something like certain animals have meaning.
这对某些东西来说非常重要，比如某些动物的含义。
So we did sloth a while ago.
我们之前做过树懒。
And it also has not only the literal meaning, but sort of like connotations.
它不仅有字面意思，还有内涵。
There are visually distinctness.
它们在视觉上有区别。
It can be recognized.
它是可以被识别的。
So this is a blocker for one of the emoji that I have worked on before.
这是我之前参与设计的一个 Emoji 的障碍。
which is cave, which is kind of hard to do.
那就是洞穴，这很难做到。
I think, you know, meaning-wise it's pretty good, but it's really hard to get a cave down in emoji sizes.
我认为，就含义而言，它非常好，但很难在 Emoji 的大小下表现出一个洞穴。
And then it filling a gap, completeness.
然后是填补空白，完整性。
So a good example for that is like, for some reason, for many years, we had red heart, yellow heart, green heart, blue heart, purple heart, and no orange heart.
一个很好的例子是，多年来，我们有红色的心、黄色的心、绿色的心、蓝色的心、紫色的心，但没有橙色的心。
So, so somewhat, so, you know, you would do the rainbow, but people would substitute the pumpkin in.
你知道，你会做彩虹，但人们会用南瓜代替。
So you would like, you know, have a, have a rainbow heart thing with a little pumpkin stuck in the middle.
所以你会想要一个彩虹心的东西，中间夹着一个南瓜。
So orange heart obviously should be added and give a sense of completeness.
所以橙色的心显然应该被添加进来，给人一种完整的感觉。
And then something else is existing vendor compatibility.
然后是与现有供应商的兼容性。
And so a good example for that was many years ago, WhatsApp decided to add the gender non-binary emoji.
一个很好的例子是，很多年前，WhatsApp 决定添加非二元性别 Emoji。
And then once it did that, then all the other kind of vendors jumped on.
然后一旦它这样做了，所有其他的供应商都跟进了。
So what kind of knocks out an emoji?
那么是什么样的 Emoji 会被淘汰呢？
So too specific or narrow. So we'll often see that with very specific animals or a very specific group.
过于具体或狭隘。所以我们经常会在非常具体的动物或非常具体的群体中看到这种情况。
It's redundant so one year, Oh, my God, who makes it? Butterball.
它是多余的，所以有一年，天哪，是谁做的？Butterball。
Butterball makes the turkeys.
Butterball 是火鸡生产商。
Butterball submitted an emoji proposal that was like a cooked turkey, but we already had a live turkey, so it seemed kind of redundant of both like a cooked turkey for Thanksgiving and a live turkey.
Butterball 提交了一个表情符号提案，图案像一只烤火鸡，
但我们已经有了活火鸡的表情，所以它看起来有点多余，感恩节已经有烤火鸡和活火鸡了。
So not visually discernible.
所以视觉上难以区分。
This is a struggle for things like, I don't know, my friends have kind of proposed kimchi
这对某些事物来说是个难题，比如，我不知道，我的朋友们提议过泡菜。
Kim Chi is really hard on emoji sizes for many reasons.
泡菜表情符号的大小很难确定，有很多原因。
And part of that tension is because it's not visually discernible.
部分原因是它在视觉上难以区分。
Then there are no logos, brands, deities, or celebrities.
还有，不能是 logo、品牌、神灵或名人。
So no Nike swoosh, no McDonald's M. And then this is one that we kind of decided in the last year or so, which is no more flags.
所以不能是耐克的 swoosh 标志，不能是麦当劳的 M。然后这是我们最近一年左右决定的，不再添加国旗。
Flags are a very complicated thing.
国旗是一个非常复杂的东西。
And as a result, Unicode does not want to be in the business of deciding what is a country or not a country.
因此，Unicode 不想参与决定什么是国家或不是国家的业务。
So, like, you know, when you get a proposal from, like, Kurdistan, you're like, yeah.
比如，当你收到来自库尔德斯坦的提案时，你会想，好吧。
So right now the way that the emoji flags are decided is they kind of depend on what the U.N. recognizes, and then those get passed down to the International Standards Organization, and then Unicode just does that.
所以现在决定表情符号国旗的方式是，它们取决于联合国的认可，然后这些国旗会被传递给国际标准化组织，然后 Unicode 只需照做。
Like, it does not want to be in the business of kind of, you know, the geopolitical affairs.
它不想卷入地缘政治事务。
So once it comes out of the subcommittee, it goes to the full Unicode Technical Committee, UTC.
所以一旦它从小组委员会出来，就会提交给 Unicode 技术委员会 (UTC)。
Those are the people that were in the room that I showed you.
这些人就是我给你们看的那间屋子里的那些人。
And they vote once a year, basically, to pass all the emoji.
他们每年投票一次，基本上就是为了通过所有的表情符号。
And it takes a while. There's a lot of coordinating with the International Standards Organization and a lot of working with the companies.
这需要一段时间。需要与国际标准化组织进行大量协调，并与各家公司进行大量合作。
And eventually, it takes a long time, but it ends up on your devices.
最终，这需要很长时间，但它会出现在你的设备上。
And that, historically, has taken about 18 to 24 months from when you put in a proposal to when you get it in.
从你提交提案到你得到它，历史上需要 18 到 24 个月。
It's going to be a little bit longer going forward, probably, is my sense as Unicode has decided to space out some of the Unicode releases.
我的感觉是，随着 Unicode 决定间隔发布一些 Unicode 版本，这个时间以后可能会更长。
So one of the weird things is how did Unicode, this non-profit organization based in California, end up controlling this global visual language?
奇怪的是，Unicode，这个位于加州的非营利组织，是如何最终控制了这个全球性的视觉语言？
So a lot of it has to do with the fact that Emoji started in Japan.
这很大程度上与 Emoji 起源于日本有关。
back in the late 1990s.
早在 20 世纪 90 年代后期。
One of the, this set from DoCoMo in 1999 is considered, is widely considered sort of like the first like color emoji set.
DoCoMo 在 1999 年推出的这套被认为是，被广泛认为是第一套彩色 Emoji。
It has been collected by the Museum of Modern Art.
它已经被纽约现代艺术博物馆收藏。
And so these, the Japanese telecom companies would use, basically would have their own sets of emoji and then there were different companies.
所以这些，日本的电信公司会使用，基本上会有自己的 Emoji 集合，然后还有不同的公司。
So they would have different sets.
所以他们会有不同的集合。
So you could basically only send these like visual characters with someone who was on your same
所以你基本上只能和使用相同网络的人发送这些视觉字符。
So it's basically equivalent of if you were on Verizon, you could only text people on Verizon with emoji.
这基本上等同于，如果你用的是 Verizon，你就只能给用 Verizon 的人发 Emoji 短信。
Or if you were on T-Mobile, you could only do that.
或者，如果你用的是 T-Mobile，你也只能这样做。
So at a certain point, they decided the Apple and Google came into Japan.
所以在某个时候，他们决定，Apple 和 Google 来到日本。
They wanted to start selling smartphones.
他们想开始销售智能手机。
And they realized that it was a hodgepodge of systems.
他们意识到这是一个大杂烩的系统。
And they wanted to unify it.
他们想统一它。
And so in 2007, they went to Unicode.
所以在 2007 年，他们找到了 Unicode。
And they're like, OK, help us unify the emoji, basically all the emojis.
他们说，好吧，帮我们统一 Emoji，基本上是所有的 Emoji。
There was a point where, like, if you were Japanese on Apple, that would be different than Japanese on DOS or, like, Chinese or Arabic.
曾经有一段时间，如果你在 Apple 上使用日语，这将不同于在 DOS 上使用日语，或者像中文或阿拉伯语。
So it drove everyone crazy, and they basically decided around the late 80s or early 1990s that they were going to come up with one standardized system that sort of encoded all characters
所以这把所有人都逼疯了，他们在 80 年代末或 90 年代初基本上决定，要建立一个标准化的系统，对所有字符进行编码。
There are three main projects.
主要有三个项目。
like that.
像那样。
So the other thing it does, it creates localization resources.
另一个作用是创建本地化资源。
So things so that you know, like, oh, if you're in this country, you're using the euro or you're using the pesos or something.
这样一来，如果你身处某个国家，就可以使用欧元、比索或其他货币。
So there's a lot of localization data that is needed depending on which geography you're using your device from.
根据你使用设备所在的地理位置，需要大量的本地化数据。
You know that the time is used this way, or dates are shown that way.
比如时间和日期的显示方式。
So that is called the Common Locale Data Repository, or CLDR, as they call it.
这被称为通用语言环境数据存储库，简称 CLDR。
And the other thing they do is they kind of maintain libraries for developers in order to do all of them.
他们还为开发人员维护了一些库，用来处理所有这些问题。
So they are not building everything from scratch. And that is called ICU.
所以他们不需要从头开始构建一切，这就是 ICU。
So it's very funny, because it's called CLDR.
这很有趣，因为它叫 CLDR。
And then one day, one of our friend's girlfriends made him this thing.
有一天，我们一个朋友的女朋友给他做了这个东西。
which she called a seal deer, because whenever he talked about CLDR, she thought he was talking about seal deers.
她称之为“海豹鹿”，因为每当他谈到 CLDR 时，她都以为他说的是“海豹鹿”。
So now this is his little mascot for Unicode-related things.
所以现在它成了他与 Unicode 相关的小吉祥物。
So how does Unicode do this?
那么 Unicode 是如何做到这一点的呢？
So it basically assigns code points, and each code point is a unique number assigned to each Unicode character.
它基本上分配代码点，每个代码点都是分配给每个 Unicode 字符的唯一数字。
So face with tears of joy,
比如“喜极而泣”的表情。
It can be written like this with a code point, or it can be written like this in terms of decimal numbers.
它可以用代码点这样写，也可以用十进制数字这样写。
And it can also be written this in binary numbers.
也可以用二进制数字这样写。
So these are all basically the same.
所以这些基本上都是一样的。
And the key thing to know, at least about Emoji, is that when your device, if you're talking your iPhone with someone who's on a laptop or an iPad or on an Android device, it's not sending the images back and forth.
至少关于 Emoji，你需要知道的是，当你的设备，
比如你的 iPhone 与一台笔记本电脑、iPad 或 Android 设备通信时，它传递的不是图像，而是数字。
It's sending just a number back and forth.
它只是来回发送一个数字。
And then locally, your phone or your laptop decides, oh,
然后在本地，你的手机或笔记本电脑会决定，
This number correlates with which image in terms of our emoji font and then pulls it up.
这个数字对应着我们 Emoji 字体中的哪个图像，然后把它调出来。
So this is really key to know why different emoji look different on different platforms.
所以这才是理解为什么不同的 Emoji 在不同的平台上看起来不同的关键所在。
So 2007 to 2010, it took about three years.
从 2007 年到 2010 年，大约花了三年时间。
But Unicode 6.0 came out with our first little baby set of Emoji.
Unicode 6.0 出现了，它包含了我们第一套小小的 Emoji。
And it just kind of hung out there for a year.
它就这样被搁置了一年。
It wasn't doing anything.
什么也没做。
So 2011, though, Apple starts adding the Emoji keyboard.
直到 2011 年，苹果公司开始添加 Emoji 键盘。
And it just explodes.
然后 Emoji 就火了。
I feel like, in some ways, Emoji were not invented.
我觉得，在某种程度上，Emoji 不是被发明出来的。
They were discovered.
而是被发现的。
They obviously touched something very, very primal, too.
它们显然触及了我们人类非常非常原始的一些东西。
to our human desire
我们人类的愿望。
The ambiguity that comes with what emoji kind of mean.
Emoji 意义上的模糊性。
And so this is one of my favorite emoji.
这是我最喜欢的 Emoji 之一。
It's sort of like an upside-down smiley face.
它有点像一个倒过来的笑脸。
Very, very ambiguous.
非常非常模棱两可。
Clearly very ambiguous, because if you start typing into Google, the top hits are like, what does it mean from a guy?
显然非常模棱两可，因为如果你开始在 Google 中输入，最热门的搜索结果是，它从一个男人那里发出来是什么意思？
What does it mean from a girl?
从一个女孩那里发出来是什么意思？
It's clearly something that a lot of people are using in complex situationships between each other.
这显然是很多人在彼此之间复杂的关系中使用的东西。
So one of the fun things is who can propose emoji.
所以有趣的事情之一是谁可以提议 Emoji。
Technically, anyone can. Anyone here can.
技术上，任何人都可以。这里任何人都可以。
Normal humans can.
正常人都可以。
We have basically Google Doc or Google Form that we throw up historically between April and August in the last two years.
过去两年，我们基本上在 4 月到 8 月期间都会发布 Google Doc 或 Google Form 表格。
And so this is one of our favorite examples.
这是我们最喜欢的例子之一。
This is Rayouf Alhumaydi. She was a 15-year-old Saudi Arabian girl who was living in Vienna at the time that she proposed
这是 Rayouf Alhumaydi。她是一位 15 岁的沙特阿拉伯女孩，提出这个建议时住在维也纳。
And then she was like Time Magazine, like coolest teens.
然后她就登上了《时代》杂志，成了最酷的青少年。
She got into Harvard and Stanford, and she went to Stanford.
她被哈佛和斯坦福录取，最后去了斯坦福。
And so this is a proposal we got.
这就是我们收到的提案。
Then there was a group of folks from Argentina who got the Mate emoji, kind of similar to their national drink.
然后是一群来自阿根廷的人，他们得到了 Mate 茶表情符号，类似于他们的国民饮料。
There was a non-profit that really wanted to get a menstruation emoji.
有一家非营利组织非常希望获得一个月经表情符号。
And so what they proposed to begin with was bloody underwear.
他们最初的提议是带血的内裤。
And I was just like, no, no, no.
我当时就想，不行，不行，不行。
So many different reasons why this is a terrible emoji.
这个表情符号太糟糕了，原因有很多。
But so we did get blood drops. And then you could do moon and blood drop, or underwear and blood drop.
但我们确实得到了血滴。然后你可以用月亮加血滴，或者内裤加血滴。
There's a lot of different ways.
有很多不同的方式。
Actually, it's really funny, because I was polling my friends beforehand what they would use to
其实很有趣，因为我之前问过我的朋友们，她们会用什么来
There was red wine, there was kind of that rose with the falling petal.
有人说是红酒，有人说是那种花瓣掉落的那种玫瑰。
And my favorite is actually my friend who used the Japanese flag as a way to indicate that she was having her period.
我最喜欢的是我的一个朋友，她用日本国旗来表示她来了月经。
So one of the biggest contributors, this skin tone emoji, appeared I think in 2015.
肤色表情符号，我认为是 2015 年出现的，它最大的贡献之一。
It was amazing. And it was proposed by a mom, Katrina Parrott.
太棒了。 它是由一位名叫 Katrina Parrott 的母亲提出的。
She's an entrepreneur and a mom who is just like at home one day and her daughter comes home and is likeI wish there were emoji that looked like me.
她是一位企业家，也是一位母亲，有一天，她女儿放学回家说“我希望有看起来像我的 Emoji”。
And her mom was like,that's great, honey.What's an emoji?
她的妈妈说：“好极了，亲爱的，什么是 Emoji？”
And so she, like me, I guess googled and just figure it out that Unicode controlled emoji.And she just came up with a proposal saying we should not only have the yellow skin tones.At that time, everything was sort of Simpson's yellow.
我猜她像我一样用谷歌搜索了一下，发现 Unicode 控制着 Emoji。
她就想出了一个建议，说我们不应该只有黄色的皮肤。在那时，所有的东西都是《辛普森一家》那样的黄色。
It's really interesting to see how race and, like, nationality are, like, depicted in different parts of the world.
看看不同地区的种族和民族是如何被描绘的，真的很有趣。
So originally in Japan, everyone was yellow.
最初在日本，每个人都是黄色的。
But these were the non... So, you know, by default everyone was just, like...
但这些是非... 你知道的，默认情况下每个人都是。
They had a couple things that were not.
他们有一些东西不是。
One was you had a blonde person.
一个是金发碧眼的人。
So there's an emoji called blonde woman or whatever that represents all Westerners.
所以有一个叫做金发女人或什么的 Emoji 来代表所有西方人。
So that was one. And then they have one that's like an Indian guy with a turban.
这是一个。然后他们有一个戴着turban的印度男人。
So that's supposed to represent Indian people.
所以这应该代表印度人。
And then there's like a guy with a little hat that's supposed to represent Chinese people.
然后还有一个戴着小帽子的男人，应该代表中国人。
So that was the Japanese view of race, which was like, default.
所以这就是日本人对种族的看法，就像默认。
Then you were like, blonde, Western, Chinese, or Indian.
然后你就像，金发碧眼的西方人、中国人或印度人。
And that is all there was.
就这些。
And obviously, in the United States, we care a lot about race.
显然，在美国，我们非常关心种族问题。
And then so she came up with a system with five skin tones, just like normal people.
所以她想出了一个有五种肤色的系统，就像普通人一样。
Some guy in Germany decided that he wanted to do a face with one eyebrow raised, or as we call it, the Colbert emoji.
德国有个人决定要做一个眉毛上挑的表情，或者我们称之为 Colbert Emoji。
Oh, this one's fun.
这个很有趣。
So women's flat shoe.
女式平底鞋。
I have to say, not highly used statistically at this point, but I really kind of appreciate it because it was a mom who was very offended that all women's shoes had heels, even the sandals.
我得说，目前统计数据显示它的使用率不高，但我真的很欣赏它，
因为它是一位妈妈提出来的，她对所有女鞋，甚至是凉鞋都有鞋跟这件事感到非常生气。
So this is her.
所以就是她。
She had like three kids at the time.
她当时好像有三个孩子。
She now has four. She was very fertile.
她现在有四个了，她很有生育能力。
And she also did the women's flat.
她也做了女式平底鞋。
OK, she also did One-piece bathing suit, because she was also offended by the fact that the only kind of bathing suit you had was this little itsy-bitsy polka-dot bikini thing, which is not great if you're taking your six-year-old.
对了，她还做了连体泳衣，因为她也对当时唯一的一种泳衣——那种小小的波点比基尼感到生气，如果你要带你六岁的孩子去的话，那就不太合适了。
So I have to say, that got passed, but it didn't go over super well with everyone.
所以不得不说，这个提议通过了，但并不是所有人都满意。
Unicode, because it's very public, submits things for comments.
Unicode 非常公开，会提交内容征求意见。
And we got this comment back.
然后我们收到了这条评论。
So one-piece bathing suit.
连体泳衣。
Why?
为什么？
A person wanting to indicate the use of swimwear can't use existing bikini?
想表达泳装的人不能用现有的比基尼吗？
Is this really necessary?
真的有必要吗？
What about a Victorian bathing costume or a wetsuit or waterworks?
那维多利亚时代的泳衣、潜水服或防水服呢？
This is like literally in like literally in like the records, and like do not encode. And so the person who did this, actually very impressive.
这就像，真的，真的记录在案了，就像“不要编码”。所以做这件事的人，真的很厉害。
He's actually the person who created the middle finger emoji. And actually if you've ever seen the Vulcan emoji, the Vulcan hand emoji, he's actually very active.
他就是创造了“竖中指”表情符号的人。实际上，如果你见过“瓦肯举手礼”表情符号，就知道他很活跃。
And I have to say, this is actually, I think, one of the more impressive emojis.
我得说，我认为这实际上是最令人印象深刻的表情符号之一。
So obviously, obviously, we have a lot of active debate.
显然，显然，我们有很多激烈的辩论。
Sometimes you get whole countries submitting.
有时候，整个国家都会提交申请。
So literally, the government of Finland, as in their equivalent of the State Department, their diplomacy kind of thing, submitted a proposal for sauna.
芬兰政府，相当于他们的国务院，他们外交部门，提交了一份关于桑拿的提案。
And these were so creepy and so weird.
这些提案非常怪异，非常奇怪。
So much is wrong with this.
这里面有很多问题。
But I felt where they were coming from.
但我明白他们的意图。
First of all, they're naked.
首先，他们是裸体的。
They have club feet.
他们的脚是畸形的。
And so we decided to help them.
所以我们决定帮助他们。
We're like, OK, we see where you're going with this.
我们想，好吧，我们明白你们的意思了。
Let's see if we can help you.
让我们看看是否能帮到你们。
We had the spoon.
我们有勺子。
Should there be steam around them?
他们周围应该有蒸汽吗？
Should they be naked or wearing a towel?
他们应该裸体还是裹着毛巾？
It was super dicey.
这非常冒险。
But we wanted to help them, because it was literally a foreign government coming in front of Unicode advocating for the sauna emoji on behalf of their entire country.
但我们想帮助他们，因为这确实是一个外国政府代表整个国家在 Unicode 面前倡导桑拿表情符号。
So then this is sort of evolved into just basically person in steamy room, which is the most sort of like the PG version of sauna.
所以这逐渐演变成基本上是人在蒸汽房里，这是最接近 PG 版本的桑拿。
And there's no spoon.
而且没有勺子。
They're all dressed. It's very odd.
他们都穿着衣服。这很奇怪。
So you can see the evolution of what it started out, what we submitted, and what it ended up.
所以你可以看到它最初的样子，我们提交的样子，以及它最终的样子。
So there's a lot of evolution throughout the entire process.
所以在整个过程中有很多演变。
And companies can submit emoji proposals, too.
公司也可以提交表情符号提案。
So Google actually worked on this one.
谷歌参与了这件事。
I love this one. OK.
我喜欢这个。
So just to give you some context, as of 2015, There are many ways you could be or have an occupation as a male on the emoji keyboard, right?
背景是，截至 2015 年，在 Emoji 键盘上，男性有很多职业选择。
Like, for example, you could be a police officer.
例如，你可以是警察。
You could be a detective.
你可以是侦探。
You could be a Buckingham Palace guard.
你可以是白金汉宫的卫兵。
You could even be Santa Claus.
你甚至可以是圣诞老人。
Like, these are so many jobs that you could have.
有很多工作可以选择。
But if you were a woman, as of 2015, there were four things that you could be.
但如果你是女性，截至 2015 年，只有四种选择。
You could be a princess.
你可以是公主。
You could be a bride.
你可以是新娘。
You could be a dancer.
你可以是舞者。
Or you could be a Playboy Bunny. These were the sum total of all the occupations that we could have.
或者你可以是花花公子兔女郎。这些就是我们可以拥有的所有职业的总和。
So there was sort of this movement at that time.
当时出现了一种运动。
There was this video on YouTube that went viral.
YouTube 上有一个视频火了。
There was a New York Times op-ed that was like, where are the women with professions?
《纽约时报》的一篇专栏文章问道：有职业的女性在哪里？
So basically, they came up with a set of emoji for professions.
他们设计了一套职业 Emoji。
And what's nice is not only did women have these professions, now men have them too.
好消息是，不仅女性有了这些职业，男性现在也有了。
So of Emoji Nation emoji, these are some of the ones that we've worked on.
在 Emoji Nation 的 Emoji 中，这些是我们参与设计的一部分。
I think about 130 of the emoji on your keyboard probably came through, touched our system in some way, including, I have to say, a microbe or virus.
我认为键盘上大约 130 个 Emoji 可能以某种方式经过了我们的系统，包括微生物或病毒。
I think I have the opinion that every emoji has its day.
我觉得每个表情符号都有它的时代。
It might not be today.
可能不是今天。
It might not be next year.
也可能不是明年。
But I have to say virus was not doing anything.
但我不得不说，病毒以前没什么用。
Then came 2020, and that was such a good moment for it, along with soap.
然后 2020 年来了，这对它来说是一个非常好的时刻，还有肥皂。
We had also done soap.
我们也做过肥皂。
So, you know, among the other emoji that we have worked on are sorry, mooncake, llama, like, teddy bear.
我们还参与过的其他表情符号有对不起、月饼、羊驼、泰迪熊。
There were no toys.
没有玩具。
I felt really sad for toys.
我为玩具感到难过。
We have, like, giraffe.
我们有长颈鹿。
There was bubble tea.
还有珍珠奶茶。
Bubble tea was very controversial, actually.
珍珠奶茶实际上很有争议。
I have to say, we tried to slide it in originally with the takeout box and the dumplings, and people were not...
我得说，我们最初想把它和外卖盒、饺子一起放进去，但人们不...
Not having it, I understand that because there's not a lot like compared to like beer or wine like bubble tea does not is not long does not have a long history on this planet.
不接受，我能理解，因为与啤酒或葡萄酒相比，珍珠奶茶在这个星球上的历史并不长。
But I will say that they submitted again actually kind of originally proposing that it was not just bubble tea but but like a black ball and milk and tea it was
但我要说的是，他们实际上是再次提交的，最初的建议是，它不只是珍珠奶茶，而像是黑球、牛奶和茶的组合，
it was kind of cool and I have to say there was definitely a generational divide between like the Asian women who sit in that room and are like this absolutely is a thing that we consume like almost like every week of our life,
这很酷，我不得不说，坐在那个房间里的亚洲女性和年龄稍大的人之间肯定存在代沟，她们几乎每周都会喝一次，
and people who are a little bit older who are like, that looks like a parfait. How do you not know that's not a parfait?
而年龄稍大的人会说，那看起来像芭菲。你怎么会不知道那不是芭菲？
We're like, we absolutely know it is not a parfait. And so it got in, eventually. So it does sort of influence. It kind of shows who is in the room influences the decisions that get made or sometimes in the room, now sometimes more likely in the Zoom.
我们会说，我们绝对知道它不是芭菲。所以它最终还是被采纳了。
这确实会产生影响。这表明谁在房间里会影响做出的决定，或者有时在房间里，现在更有可能是在 Zoom 里。
I actually had to say Beaver emoji, if you see Beaver emoji, that's one of the ones I'm most proud of. So that is actually co-authored by a professor here at Harvard who is both lesbian and was married to a woman from Canada.
我必须得说一下海狸表情，如果你看到海狸表情，那是我最自豪的表情之一。
它实际上是哈佛大学一位教授与人合著的，她既是女同性恋，又嫁给了加拿大的一位女性。
So it was very important to her to get the beaver emoji passed.
所以对她来说，通过海狸表情非常重要。
And she promised me it would always be the first line of her bio.
她向我保证，这将永远是她个人简介的第一句话。
And indeed, if you go to her Twitter handle, it's like, Joan Donovan, creator of the beaver emoji, comma, is head of research at the Shorenstein Center at the Harvard Kennedy School.
事实上，如果你去看她的推特账号，就会发现，上面写着：Joan Donovan，海狸表情符号的创造者，是哈佛大学肯尼迪学院肖恩斯坦中心的主任。
It's pretty impressive.
这相当令人印象深刻。
And then we did greens.
然后我们做了蔬菜。
Actually, greens was really interesting because People were like, why do we need greens?
事实上，蔬菜很有趣，因为人们会问，为什么我们需要蔬菜？
We have salad.
我们有沙拉。
And I was like, we're Chinese.
我会说，我们是中国人。
We don't eat raw greens.
我们不吃生蔬菜。
Because you don't know where it's been or if it's clean.
因为你不知道它来自哪里，也不知道它是否干净。
So we cook our greens.
所以我们会把蔬菜煮熟。
So salad is not something that we have.
所以我们不吃沙拉。
So eventually I got my greens.
所以最后我得到了我的蔬菜。
And so that was kind of fun.
这还挺有趣的。
And then so these are some of the people who sort of have contributed to our little emoji nation things.
这些就是为我们的小表情符号国家做出贡献的人。
including a number of Native Americans who helped get feathered.
包括一些帮助设计羽毛的美国原住民。
So why do I care?
我为什么要关心这个？
So part of it is because I'm Chinese.
一部分原因是因为我是中国人。
I grew up speaking Chinese and English at the same time. And it's really interesting to see Chinese and English characters in terms of emoji and Chinese together. So this is fire.
我从小就同时说中文和英文。看到中文、英文字符以及表情符号和中文同时出现，真的很有趣。这就是“火”。
You have fire characters, and now you have the emoji things.
你有“火”字，现在你还有了表情符号。
And it kind of shows that there is a longevity in the human experience of something that was designed 4,000 years ago as the same visual cues in the human experiences as now.
这表明，4000年前设计的视觉符号和现在在人类体验中具有相同的意义，这体现了人类体验的持久性。
So mouth. Tree, moon, sun.
比如嘴，树，月亮，太阳。
You can mix and match them, which is super fun.
你可以把它们混合搭配，这超级有趣。
So, you know, two trees kind of make a forest.
两棵树就组成一片森林了。
Oops, sorry.
哎呀，抱歉。
Oh, well, okay.
好吧。
Then the moon and sun together means bright, which I like.
月亮和太阳在一起表示明亮，我喜欢这个。
I like this one.
我喜欢这个。
So if you stop and you think about this.
如果你停下来想一想。
So this is basically a pig.
这基本上是一头猪。
under a roof.
在屋顶下。
And what does that mean?
这意味着什么？
It does not mean farm, as you might think.
它并不像你想象的那样意味着农场。
It actually means home or family.
它实际上意味着家或家庭。
So in the Chinese kind of structure and outlook on the view, it's like where you keep your pigs is actually where your home is and what your farm is.
所以在中国的结构和观念中，养猪的地方实际上就是你的家和农场所在的地方。
So it gets kind of weird in all kinds of ways.
所以它在各种方面都变得有点奇怪。
So one of my favorite radicals, so this character means woman, 女, and
我最喜欢的偏旁部首之一，这个字的意思是女人，女，而且
As I was learning Chinese, you kind of noticed how it shows up.
在我学习中文的时候，你会注意到它是如何出现的。
So this is a woman underneath a roof.
这是一个在屋顶下的女人。
And you're like, oh, it means mom or wife or whatever, like home.
你会想，它的意思是妈妈、妻子之类的，像家一样。
It does not.
并不是。
It means peace.
它的意思是和平。
because things are at home when the woman is, or things are at peace when the woman is at home underneath a roof, which I always thought was a little bit odd.
因为当女人在家的时候，事情才安定，或者当女人在家里的屋檐下的时候，事情才太平，我一直觉得这有点奇怪。
Then there is also woman plus child.
然后还有女人加孩子。
So you're like, oh, and actually specifically boy child, the connotation there is a little bit unclear.
你会想，实际上特指男孩，这里的含义有点不清楚。
So you're like woman plus child, family, mom, you know, whatever.
你会觉得，女人加孩子，家庭，母亲，等等。
It is not, it means good.
它不是，它的意思是好。
So the standard for goodness in ancient China was a woman who had a male child.
所以在古代中国，好女人的标准是有一个男孩。
So that kind of And then, you know, three women together means evil, which is very like Macbeth.
所以这种…三个女人在一起意味着邪恶，这很像麦克白。
This character means greed.
这个字代表贪婪。
This character means slave.
这个字代表奴隶。
I think this one is jealousy.
我认为这个是嫉妒。
And this means adultery or betrayal.
这个代表通奸或背叛。
So definitely not loving the way women were portrayed on the emoji keyboard.
所以我绝对不喜欢女性在表情符号键盘上的 portray 方式。
So in case you're wondering, we just came out with a kid's book called Hadmoji that kind of compares emoji and Chinese.
如果你想知道的话，我们刚出版了一本名为 Hadmoji 的儿童读物，它对比了 Emoji 和中文。
And I think they sent out a bunch of books so that you guys can do some kind of contest later on with CS50.
我认为他们发放了很多书，这样你们以后就可以和 CS50 一起举办某种比赛。
But the mixing and matching is really interesting, right?
但这种混合搭配真的很有趣，对吧？
For example, the skin tones are actually I took my lessons from Chinese in terms of seeing how things can be fine.
例如，肤色实际上，我从中文中吸取了教训，了解到事物如何才能和谐相处。
So there's something you should know about, which is ZWIDGE.
所以你应该知道一件事，那就是 ZWIDGE。
This is also an invisible emoji character.
这也是一个不可见的表情符号字符。
It stands for zero with joiner.
它代表零宽度连接符。
And it was actually originally created mostly for Arabic
它最初主要是为阿拉伯语创建的。
where you would basically kind of force something to be in the beginning of a word or an end of a word by kind of having this invisible character.
你可以强制某个东西出现在单词的开头或结尾，方法是用这种不可见的字符。
So the rainbow flag, for example, is actually a rainbow plus the white flag.
例如，彩虹旗实际上是彩虹加上白旗。
And we could have all kinds of fun combinations.
我们可以有很多有趣的组合。
If you look at polar bear, it actually is, if you have an older device where it breaks apart, it is bear plus snow, which is really cute.
如果你看北极熊，它实际上是，如果你有一个旧设备，它会分开，它是熊加雪，这真的很可爱。
Originally, I had bear plus white.
最初，我有熊加白色。
And then we decided that Bear plus Snow made a lot more sense.
后来我们决定熊加雪更有意义。
So another one.
所以另一个。
This is new.
这是新的。
I think you guys should have it if you've updated your phones in the last year or so.
我想如果你们在过去一年左右更新了手机，你们应该会有这个。
So Mending Heart is Heart plus Band-Aid.
所以愈合的心是心加创可贴。
What is this one?
这是什么？
Oh, this is interesting.
这很有趣。
There was a breastfeeding woman for a long time and people felt like there was not gender parity.
很长一段时间以来，都有一个母乳喂养的妇女，人们觉得没有性别平等。
It was actually really interesting. All the people who wrote in were like, I want to be a dad showing that I'm holding my baby.
这真的很有趣，所有写信来的人都说，我想成为一个爸爸，表明我抱着我的孩子。
Why is there only a woman holding my baby? So we kind of created a whole set.
为什么只有女人抱着我的孩子？所以我们创造了一整套。
So this is man plus model.
所以这是男人加模特。
And all of these occupations are actually oftentimes a woman plus the fried egg or a school or a tractor.
所有这些职业实际上通常是一个女人加上煎蛋或学校或拖拉机。
And that's how you got the occupations.
这就是你如何获得职业。
If you send an emoji over into an older system, sometimes it will break apart.
如果你将一个 Emoji 发送到旧系统，有时它会分开。
So one of my kind of favorite kind of contributions in this in this world is interracial couple emoji, which we did with Tinder, which is super fun, because then you could have, you know, different couples that are and like so many common.
在这个世界上，我最喜欢的一种贡献是跨种族情侣 Emoji，
我们和 Tinder 一起做的，超级有趣，因为你可以有，你知道，不同的情侣，就像很多常见的。
This is like this is a fun if you guys ever have to do a combinatoric test.
如果你们有人做过组合测试，就会觉得这很有趣。
This is really fun, because you have two genders, plus a third neutral gender, plus two people, plus five skin tones, plus yellow.
真的很有意思，因为你有两种性别，再加上第三种中性性别，再加上两个人，再加上五种肤色，再加上黄色。
How many emoji couples can you come up with when you introduce this factor?
当你引入这个因素时，你能想出多少种表情符号组合？
And underneath it, it's just a switch sequence.
在其下面，它只是一个开关序列。
It's like two people standing together that are glued together.
就像两个站在一起的人被粘在一起了。
Now, this actually gets interesting from a CS50 perspective, because in many cases, even though you only see one character, underneath the hood depending on how your system works, they're counting each one of these as an individual character.
现在，从 CS50 的角度来看，这实际上变得有趣了，因为在很多情况下，
即使你只看到一个字符，但在底层，根据系统的不同，它们会将每一个字符都算作一个独立的字符。
So your string length actually might be five instead of one. And this kind of became a problem with things like Twitter where things had a hard skin length.
所以你的字符串长度实际上可能是 5 而不是 1。这在 Twitter 之类的东西上就成了一个问题，因为它们对字符串长度有限制。
So gender inclusivity is actually one of the things that we've been dealing most with in the last couple of years.
因此，性别包容性实际上是我们过去几年一直在处理的事情之一。
So, it's kind of interesting if you think about both what a pictorial language looks like versus the abstractness of a spoken language.
如果你想想图画语言和口语的抽象性，就会觉得很有趣。
So, because, you know, we had boy and we had girl.
因为，我们有男孩，我们有女孩。
But there was no way to say generic child, right?
但没有办法说通用的孩子，对吧？
Like, if you want to say child, you had to pick a boy or a girl, but not a way to say, like, just some little person.
比如，如果你想说孩子，你必须选择男孩或女孩，但没有办法说，只是一个小孩。
And that's really key, because in English, at least, there is no gender applied by child.
这真的很关键，因为至少在英语中，孩子是没有性别之分的。
So how do we mimic that?
那我们如何模仿呢？
And it also is key for something like doctor, right?
对于医生来说，这也很关键，对吧？
Doctor and teacher.
医生和老师。
Those don't have gender implied, but when we have them on the emoji keyboard, you have to pick a male teacher or, you know, a female doctor or whatnot.
这些都没有暗示性别，但当我们在表情符号键盘上使用它们时，你必须选择男老师或女医生等等。
So there was actually a guy at Adobe who considers himself non-gender binary, also the man behind the orange
所以在 Adobe 真的有一个人，他认为自己是非二元性别者，也是橙色背后的男人
the orange heart, he fought and got basically the first three non-gender binary emojis.
橙色心的背后的人，他努力争取，并最终获得了前三个非二元性别的表情符号。
So child, adult, and older adult.
所以有孩子、成年人和老年人。
So those are created.
这些表情符号就是这样被创造出来的。
And then we started having to propagate them through actually all the occupations.
然后我们开始必须将它们推广到所有职业中。
So these are the gender-neutral versions of many of those.
所以这些是其中许多表情符号的中性版本。
But then we got into this whole thing where every emoji that had a gender originally had to be mirrored.
但后来我们遇到了这个问题，每个最初有性别区分的表情符号都必须被镜像。
So originally we had bearded man, and then we're like, okay, well, we actually have to get bearded woman.
最初我们有大胡子男人，然后我们想，好吧，我们还得有个大胡子女。
So that is on your keyboard.
所以这个表情符号在你的键盘上。
There is pregnant woman.
有孕妇。
There is now pregnant man, which is interesting.
现在有孕妇了，这很有趣。
There is, you know, woman in a bridal gown.
还有穿婚纱的女人。
There is now man in a bridal gown.
现在有穿婚纱的男人了。
And then there were ones that actually had to be created that were neither man or woman.
还有一些表情符号必须被创造出来，它们既不是男人也不是女人。
So this is a mer-person.
这是一个美人鱼。
So there was mer-man, there was mer-maid, and there was mer-person.
之前有男美人鱼，女美人鱼，现在有中性美人鱼。
It was really interesting to figure out, like, how do you draw a gender-neutral mer-person?
弄清楚如何画一个性别中立的美人鱼真的很有趣。
Like, a bunch of them in the beginning actually had the arms crossed around sort of the chest.
一开始，很多美人鱼实际上都是双臂交叉在胸前。
Monarch, so there was Prince and Princess, and now there is Monarch.
君主，以前有王子和公主，现在有君主了。
And one of my favorite actually is there was Santa Claus, and there was Mrs. Claus, and now there's MX Claus.
我最喜欢的一个是，以前有圣诞老人，圣诞老奶奶，现在有MX圣诞老人。
Like the name of this character literally in Unicode is MX Claus.
Unicode 中这个角色的名字实际上是 MX Claus。
So I feel like it's sort of like a very official enshrining of gender non-binary-ness in like the world.
所以我觉得这有点像是在全世界范围内正式 enshrining 性别非二元性。
Not everyone loved it. New York Post did not love this.
不是每个人都喜欢这样。《纽约邮报》就不喜欢。
They were like, we're turning into emoji woke wars.
他们就像在说，我们正在变成表情符号觉醒战争。
So some emoji stats for you.
这里有一些关于表情符号的数据。
This is very fascinating.
这非常有意思。
This is sort of like the general distribution.
这有点像总体分布。
By far, the single emoji that you use more than anything else is the face with tears of joy.
到目前为止，使用最多的单个表情符号是“喜极而泣”的脸。
About 10% of all emoji sent is that one character.
大约 10% 的表情符号发送量都是这个字符。
And then number two is heart, red heart.
然后第二名是心形，红心。
And then it kind of goes down.
然后就逐渐下降了。
So there's a frequency of emoji use.
所以表情符号的使用频率是这样的。
This is sort of done by Order of magnitude.
这有点像按数量级排列的。
So 1 is half of 2, 2 is half of 1.
所以 1 是 2 的一半，2 是 1 的一半。
So it's really interesting.
这真的很有趣。
It's a very, very steep drop-off after the first couple.
在前几个之后，它是一个非常非常陡峭的下降趋势。
In case you ever want to go onto the Emoji Unicode website, you too can see all the frequency things.
如果你想访问 Emoji Unicode 网站，你也可以看到所有关于频率的内容。
So I think it's really funny.
我觉得这真的很有趣。
So basically if it's green going this way, it increased in usage between 2019 and 2021.
所以基本上，如果它是绿色向这边走，就表示它在 2019 年到 2021 年间使用量增加了。
If it's red going this way, it dropped.
如果它是红色向这边走，就表示它下降了。
And so pleading face, which is a relatively new emoji, just sort of shot up on the charts.
所以“恳求脸”是一个相对较新的表情符号，它在排行榜上的排名直线上升。
And whereas actually like smiling face with heart eyes actually is like kind of split, which is interesting.
而实际上像“心形眼睛的笑脸”实际上有点分裂，这很有趣。
So we just closed our emoji proposal round for 2022.
我们刚刚结束了 2022 年的表情符号提案征集。
These were sort of the breakdowns.
这些是分类。
People love submitting smileys and food and beverages, animals and nature.
人们喜欢提交表情符号、食物、饮料、动物和自然。
I mean, these are very Googly colors.
我的意思是，这些都是非常 Google 的颜色。
So what is the future of emoji?
那么 Emoji 的未来是什么？
I will tell you, because we just had a meeting two weeks ago, so I can now publicly talk about it.
我可以告诉你，因为我们两周前刚开过会，所以现在可以公开谈论了。
So historically, there was this whole idea, like, Unico doesn't want to be in the world of like encoding glyphs for devices everywhere.
从历史上看，一直有这样一个想法，Unicode 不想为所有设备编码字形。
There was a very controversial one when I started doing that. Because mostly what Unicode used to do was take an existing language, could be dead, and then it would just take it and digitize it.
当我开始做这件事的时候，有一个很有争议的问题。
因为 Unicode 过去的主要工作是采用一种现有的语言，可以是已经消亡的语言，然后对其进行数字化。
It took languages that existed and just digitized them.
它采用现有的语言，并将它们数字化。
And then when it kind of wandered into emoji world, suddenly it's like deciding what deserves to be an emoji, decides to be digitized.
当它进入 Emoji 世界时，突然之间，它就像决定什么应该成为 Emoji，决定什么应该被数字化。
Thank you.
谢谢。
a way to send pictures back and forth where you, it's a fixed picture and you like use a hash so that you know, we would look at the picture and then like go do a lookup somewhere.
一种来回发送图片的方式，它是一个固定的图片，你需要使用一个哈希值，以便你知道，我们会查看图片，然后去某个地方查找。
Like that did not go over well.
这并没有得到很好的认可。
Then there was actually a really interesting proposal I kind of like, didn't go over well, which is using something called a QID, which is in the Wikipedia world.
然后实际上有一个我非常喜欢的提议，但没有得到很好的认可，那就是使用一种叫做 QID 的东西，它存在于维基百科的世界里。
So in Wikipedia world, items all have numbers across the different language wikipedia.
所以在维基百科的世界里，所有条目在不同语言的维基百科中都有编号。
So Obama, human, Earth, they will have an ID number,so that the page in English and the page in German the page in Chinese all know that they're pointing to the same thing.
所以奥巴马、人类、地球，他们都会有一个 ID 号码，这样英语页面、德语页面和中文页面都知道它们指向的是同一个东西。
So the question, so one idea came up, like why don't we use the numbering system so we can use like Eiffel tower and see the number and then like, oh, people know like  oh you're, trying to say Eiffel tower.
所以问题是，有人提出，为什么我们不使用编号系统呢？
这样我们就可以使用像埃菲尔铁塔这样的东西，看到它的编号，然后人们就会明白，你想说的是埃菲尔铁塔。
That did not go over well. So both of those proposals seem dead as of yet. And it's too bad because you'll see what's happening.
这并没有得到很好的认可。所以到目前为止，这两个提议似乎都已经被否决了。这太糟糕了，因为你会看到接下来发生的事情。
So what's coming in 2022? So these are the emoji that I actually sort of thought they would be on your phones by now because we're in mid-November and they usually update early November. So three more hearts. People love hearts.
那么 2022 年会有什么新东西呢？这些 Emoji 我原本以为现在应该已经在你们的手机上了，
因为现在已经是 11 月中旬了，它们通常会在 11 月初更新。所以多了三个心形。人们喜欢心形。
Wing, Blackbird, Goose, Birds, Purple Flowers, Jellyfish, Moose Face, Donkey, Ginger, Peapod, Wireless, Conda, Shaking Face, Folding Hand Fan.
翅膀、黑鸟、鹅、鸟类、紫色花朵、水母、驼鹿脸、驴、生姜、豆荚、无线、康达、颤抖的脸、折叠扇。
That one was interesting because when people first proposed it, they proposed it as an electric fan. Who knows what electro fans will look like in 100 years.
那一个很有趣，因为当人们第一次提出它的时候，他们把它叫做电风扇。谁知道 100 年后电风扇会是什么样子。
The curly hair that they introduced a couple years ago was supposed to do that, and most of the vendors actually have it in a sort of Afro-y way,
几年前他们推出的卷发本来应该是这样的，而且大多数供应商实际上都把它设计成 Afro-y 的样子，
except for Apple, so there's a lot of complaints, but hairpick was sort of an interesting way, it means both comb, but also has sort of an interesting historic connotation, and it's been around for about 2,000 years.
除了苹果，所以有很多抱怨，但“hairpick（发梳）”这个词很有趣，它既指梳子，也有有趣的的历史内涵，而且它已经存在了大约 2000 年。
A couple of music things, maracas and flute.
还有一些音乐方面的东西，沙球和长笛。
Beyond 2022, one of the things that's gonna die, oops, can I go back?
展望 2022 年以后，有一样东西要消失了，哎呀，我可以回去吗？
No, I can't.
不行，我回不去了。
Oh, well.
哦，好吧。
We're going to retire the family emoji.
我们要淘汰家庭表情符号了。
They didn't go over so well.
它们不太受欢迎。
There were so many of them.
它们太多了。
Combinatorically, if you had everything in all the races, because you wanted to have skin tones, because you didn't want to imply that families can only be one race.
从组合的角度来看，如果你想在所有种族中都包含所有东西，因为你想要有肤色，因为你不想暗示家庭只能是单一种族。
It was such an ordeal.
这真是太难了。
Essentially, we're all like, no one uses them.
基本上，我们都觉得，没人用它们。
And there are so many.
而且它们太多了。
And it's like the fonts, in terms of the load, is too large.
而且就像字体一样，就负载而言，太大了。
so they're just going to make them all into like basically little like bathroom symbol type folks. So I think that is, those will disappear. What's actually really interesting about the family emoji is they had gay fam.
所以他们基本上会把这些都变成像卫生间符号那样的小图标。我认为，那些将会消失。关于家庭表情符号，真正有趣的是他们引入了同性恋家庭表情符号。
When they introduced the family emoji, they had gay family emoji, and the Russian government went berserk.
当他们推出家庭表情符号时，他们也有同性恋家庭表情符号，结果俄罗斯政府大发雷霆。
And actually you can Google this in 2015, you'll see a bunch of articles about the Russian government considering it homosexual propaganda to use. And there was a big debate about whether or not they were going to ban Apple devices.
你实际上可以在2015年谷歌一下，你会看到许多关于俄罗斯政府认为使用这些符号是同性恋宣传的文章。甚至还有一场关于是否禁止苹果设备的大辩论。
And so you can see a lot of the media coverage from that time. But I thought it was really interesting how upset a national government can get about little pictures on your phone.
所以你可以看到那段时间的许多媒体报道。但我觉得一个国家政府会对手机上的小图片如此愤怒真的很有趣。
Another thing that's on the agenda as of a couple of weeks ago is directionality in terms of emoji.
还有一件事是几周前提上议程的，那就是表情符号的方向性。
So as you know, most emoji kind of just flip one way or another.
如你所知，大多数表情符号只能朝一个方向翻转。
And the reason why it matters is because not all languages run in the same direction.
原因是，并非所有语言的书写方向都相同。
So for example, Arabic.
例如，阿拉伯语。
So we are used to left to right, but a lot of languages go right to left.
我们习惯于从左到右，但很多语言是从右到左的。
And this kind of changes the meaning of emoji.
这有点改变了表情符号的意义。
For example, right to left.
例如，从右到左。
I send this a lot to my friends when I'm going flying from the Bay Area to New York.
当我从湾区飞往纽约时，我经常把这个发给我的朋友。
If you do it from left to right, however, that is what it looks like.
但如果从左到右看，就是这样。
So it looks like you're in a Bay Area, but the plane is still going up and to the right.
所以看起来你像是在湾区，但飞机还在向上向右飞。
And then now it looks like you're going from New York to the Bay Area.
现在看起来像是你要从纽约飞往湾区。
The other place is like, oh, it's a girl, and she's running really fast.
另一个例子是，这是一个女孩，她跑得真快。
That is right to left in our world.
在我们的世界里，那是从右到左的。
And in here, it would be, she's, like, behind, like, pollution or something like that.
而在在这里，她就像在污染或类似的东西后面。
So sorry about that.
很抱歉。
So an example, this is actually in the proposal.
举个例子，这实际上是在提案中。
Like, in one case, if it's left to right, you're running away from a line of cars.
比如，在一种情况下，如果它是从左到右的，你就是在躲避一排汽车。
In the other one, it's a warning to not run behind car fumes.
在另一种情况下，这是一个警告，不要在汽车尾气后面跑。
So they are trying to figure out, like, how do we mirror a bunch of the emoji?
所以他们正在试图弄清楚，如何镜像一堆表情符号。
But the main thing that I don't know when it's going to happen.
但我不知道什么时候会发生。
I'm really hopeful it's going to happen.
我真的希望它会发生。
It's trying to come up with a system that supports little stickers in line that don't need Unicode.
它试图想出一个系统，支持在行内使用不需要 Unicode 的小贴纸。
So this is like Slack or on Twitch.
就像 Slack 或 Twitch。
You can embed little pictures in line, and all the vendors have to get together and agree to come up with a standard way to do that.
你可以在行内嵌入小图片，所有供应商都必须达成一致，想出一个标准的方法来实现这一点。
They have not yet come up with that.
他们还没有想出办法。
But that is sort of one of the ways that Unicode wants to back away from actually being a global regulator for little colorful glyphs.
但这算是 Unicode 不想成为彩色小字形全球监管者的方式之一。
And so if you ever need to reach me in my emoji world, you can find me at Jenny at Emojination.org.
所以如果想在我的 Emoji 世界里找到我，可以访问 Jenny@Emojination.org。
It will be actually a while, I think, before we see a next generation of Emoji showing up.
我认为，下一代 Emoji 出现还需要一段时间。
It used to be like every year they would get new code points.
以前每年都会有新的代码点。
It might be a little bit less than every year now as they work on things like directionality over time.
现在可能不到一年一次了，因为他们一直在研究方向性之类的问题。
So that, if anyone has questions, you can ask questions.
如果大家有问题，现在可以提问。
You can find me afterwards.
之后也可以找到我。
I think I feel like there's supposed to be some hubbub right now about maybe, maybe
我觉得现在应该会有一些关于...的讨论
Microphones, but maybe not, but maybe I'm just done.
麦克风，也许没有，也许我已经说完了。
And if there are questions or if David is around, I'm happy to answer any questions that folks have.
如果有问题，或者 David 在的话，我很乐意回答大家的问题。
Yes.
好的。
So the question is, what are my thoughts on the emoji movie?
你对 Emoji 电影有什么看法？
You're talking about the Sony animated one.
你说的是索尼的动画片吗？
Yes.
是的。
OK.
好的。
My thought on that is it is better than a 6% rating on Rotten Tomatoes would lead you to believe.
我认为它比烂番茄 6% 的评分要好。
So that's my one thought.
这就是我的一个想法。
And my next thought is that that was a rush job from an animation perspective.
我的另一个想法是，从动画的角度来看，这是一部仓促之作。
That was about 18 months, whereas a typical animated movie takes four years.
只用了大约 18 个月，而一部典型的动画电影需要四年时间。
So in my spare time, I also produce movies and documentaries.
在我的业余时间，我也会制作电影和纪录片。
So one thing that is key to know about movies and animated movies, and this is very important, they take a very long time, but you can always fix it because you haven't shot anything.
制作电影，尤其是动画电影，需要知道的一件重要的事是，它们需要很长时间才能完成，但你总能进行修改，因为你还没有拍摄任何东西。
And a very good example of that is I assume you guys have seen Frozen.
我估计你们都看过《冰雪奇缘》，这就是一个很好的例子。
If you haven't seen Frozen, you've seen him of the age that you would have seen Frozen.
如果你没看过《冰雪奇缘》，那你也到了应该看它的年纪了。
I do not understand how huge a phenomenon or why it was such a huge phenomenon.
我不明白它为什么，以及是如何成为一个如此巨大的现象的。
They actually did an original cut of Frozen.
他们实际上制作了《冰雪奇缘》的原始版本。
So I don't know if you guys know the Snow Queen thing, but she's super dark and not fun and kind of evil and not someone you want to get behind as a character.
我不知道你们是否了解“冰雪女王”的故事，但她超级黑暗，一点也不有趣，而且有点邪恶，不是你想支持的角色。
So they actually did a rough cut of that, of Frozen.
他们实际上制作了《冰雪奇缘》的粗剪版。
And they came out of that with, it's just storyboarding.
他们完成了故事板，从粗剪版中走了出来。
And they were like, that is not good.
然后他们觉得，这不行。
And they killed it.
他们放弃了。
They were like, we can't go with this.
他们觉得，不能继续这样下去。
And then started from scratch, more or less, again, starting with a song, Let It Go, which is actually written by a kid from my elementary school, Bobby Lopez, or co-written by Bobby Lopez.
然后他们几乎是从头再来，从一首叫做《Let It Go》的歌开始，这首歌实际上是由我小学同学 Bobby Lopez 创作的，或者说是与他共同创作的。
I also, actually, fun fact, I also went, I took the school bus with Lin Manuel Miranda.
另外，说个有趣的事实，我和 Lin Manuel Miranda 乘坐同一辆校车。
So I was a fourth grader when he was like a kindergartner.
我上四年级的时候，他好像在上幼儿园。
So we had a very musical elementary school in New York City.
所以我们在纽约市的这所小学里有很多音乐方面的人才。
But the thing is, they could fix it because they had enough time and have enough money.
但关键是，他们可以进行修改，因为他们有足够的时间和资金。
Movies where you shoot humans, much harder to fix.
而拍摄真人电影就很难修改了。
You have the footage that you have, and you can do little pickups, but you can't fix it.
你只能利用已有的素材，虽然可以进行一些补拍，但无法进行大的修改。
So essentially what happened in that case, I think it's 18 months, and it could have gotten better.
所以基本上，这种情况，我认为是 18 个月，本来可以做得更好。
And a lot of the movies that you see with Pixar, it's actually sort of emotionally similar to the movie called Inside Out.
你看到的很多皮克斯电影，其实在情感上都和《头脑特工队》这部电影很相似。
And but inside, they just have more time.
但是他们内部有更多时间。
And so it's better.
所以它更好。
So as opposed to 18 months, which is not long enough to make an animated movie.
相对于 18 个月来说，这对于制作一部动画电影来说是不够的。
But the other fun thing is it was so weird, because they sold sponsorships.
但另一个有趣的事情是，这太奇怪了，因为他们出售赞助。
It was like, oh my god, here comes the bots and the malware.
就好像，我的天啊，机器人和恶意软件来了。
Let's go into Dropbox and protect ourselves.
我们去 Dropbox 保护自己吧。
And so I think that it got a lot of bad kind of vibes from the press for doing things like that.
所以我认为它因为做那样的事情从媒体那里得到了很多负面的评价。
But from a kid's perspective, it's fine.
但从孩子的角度来看，这很好。
I don't know that I would put it on my top.
我不认为我会把它列入我的前十。
10 of animated pictures, but it's better than 6% on Rotten Tomatoes.
10 部动画片，但它比烂番茄上的 6% 好。
And then actually, if you guys ever care, we have done, I did a documentary about Emoji, and all the people that helped create Emoji.
实际上，如果你们感兴趣的话，我们做过一部关于 Emoji 的纪录片，关于所有帮助创造 Emoji 的人。
And we did a CS50X movie night, I think, during the pandemic.
而且我认为，在大流行期间，我们还举办了一场 CS50X 电影之夜。
Was it during the pandemic? Everything sort of like blurred together, but it was during the pandemic.
是在大流行期间吗？所有事情都变得模糊了，但那是在大流行期间。
Yeah.
是的。
Are we, more questions?
还有其他问题吗？
Yes.
是的。
Or there's demand, yeah.
或者说有需求，是的。
Yeah, that's a very good question. So the question is, one of our criteria of getting an emoji accepted is to demonstrate demand.
是的，这是一个很好的问题。我们的 Emoji 采用标准之一是证明其需求。
And how do we demonstrate demand?
我们如何证明需求？
And I would say it's in a pretty clumsy way, actually, at this point.
我想说，在这一点上，方式相当笨拙。
So the main thing that you have in our current proposal
我们目前提议的主要内容
process is we have a median emoji, which is elephant.
是我们有一个中位表情符号，就是大象。
So elephant is like if you stack-ranked all the emoji for popularity, elephant is like right there in the middle.
大象就像，如果你把所有表情符号按流行度排名，大象就在中间。
And it's also a concept that's like universally understood across all languages.
而且它也是一个所有语言都能理解的概念。
So elephant shows up somewhere between 500 million and 700 million in Google search results.
在 Google 搜索结果中，大象的出现次数在 5 亿到 7 亿之间。
Like if you type it into a laptop, you'll see elephant, 500 million search results.
如果你把它输入笔记本电脑，你会看到大象，5 亿个搜索结果。
And generally, when you're comparing your term to elephant, you want to see very roughly how many Google search results, Bing search results, sometimes Instagram.
一般来说，当你将你的词语与大象进行比较时，你会想大致看看有多少个 Google 搜索结果、Bing 搜索结果，有时还有 Instagram。
So actually, something that was really surprising to me was someone proposed Hummingbird.
事实上，令我感到非常惊讶的是，有人提议用蜂鸟。
I think Hummingbird is a good proposal.
我认为蜂鸟是一个很好的提议。
But if you look at Hummingbird, it's only like 21 million in terms of the stats, which I thought was very surprisingly low.
但如果你看一下蜂鸟，从统计数据来看，它只有 2100 万，我认为这个数字低得惊人。
So that's one of the main ways that we kind of see, like, is it also visually used and all of that, yeah.
所以这是我们判断它是否也被视觉化使用等等的主要方法之一。
Any other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
Are we good?
都明白了吗？
I didn't even need my water or anything.
我连水都没喝。
Oh, can I take, and I'm gonna take a picture.
我可以拍张照片吗？
I'm gonna take a picture for, because now you guys are actually human and not Muppets, so I'm very, very excited about this.
我要拍张照片，因为现在你们是真人，而不是布偶，所以我非常非常激动。
So I will send this to, like, my block mates and be like, I just lectured at CS, you know, at Sanders Theater.
我要把这张照片发给我的室友们，告诉他们我刚刚在桑德斯剧院的 CS 上课了。
All right, well, my thanks to Jenny Lee.
好了，感谢 Jenny Lee。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Give me one second.
稍等。
So if up until now, I thought it would be appropriate to toss this up on the board, if up until now you've not yet gotten a CS50 stress ball on the way up, please do grab one.
如果到目前为止，你还没有在路上拿到 CS50 解压球，请拿一个，我觉得现在是时候把这个扔到黑板上了。
We've got some extras as well off to the side.
旁边还有一些额外的。
But I would also keep in mind, back in week zero, where again we began, we asked you to categorize yourselves as to whether you are among those less comfortable, those more comfortable, or those somewhere in between.
我还记得在零周，也就是我们开始的地方，我们要求你根据自己的舒适程度进行分类，是不太适应、比较适应，还是介于两者之间。
Please know now that you are officially all some
现在请记住，你们所有人正式地...
Please know now that you are all officially among those more comfortable.
现在请记住，你们现在都正式地属于比较适应的那一类了。
And indeed, even though a couple of more milestones await, we cannot wait to see what you accomplish with your final projects.
确实，即使还有一些里程碑在等着我们，我们也迫不及待地想看看你们在期末项目中会取得什么成就。
In the meantime, as always, this is and now this was CS50.
同时，一如既往，这就是 CS50，现在也依然是。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Mr. Sandman, when I enrolled in CS50, I'll say truth be told, I thought I'd be a real coding hero, because I did so well on P, he said zero.
睡魔先生，我说实话，当我报名参加 CS50 的时候，我以为我会成为一个真正的代码英雄，因为我在 P 语言上做得很好，他说零。
It picked up so fast, turns out that C is harder than Scratch.
它发展得如此之快，结果是 C 比 Scratch 难。
Hello, world, and goodbye, sleep, because this is CS50.
你好，世界，再见，睡眠，因为这是 CS50。
Mr. Sandman, I was on the Valgrind.
睡魔先生，我在用 Valgrind。
Trying so hard to not fall behind.
努力不让自己落后。
Attending section and wanting a tutor.
参加课程，想要一个助教。
Stuck in the int main void of my computer.
被困在我的电脑的 int main void 中。
Sandman, finally getting ahead.
睡魔先生，终于领先了。
Then Malin switches to Python instead.
然后 Malin 转而使用 Python。
Why we spend five weeks on C?
为什么我们要花五周时间学习 C？
Because this is CS50.
因为这是 CS50。
Mr. Sandman, we completed each task.
睡魔先生，我们完成了每一项任务。
JavaScript, SQL, CSS, and Flask.
JavaScript、SQL、CSS 和 Flask。
With every language, our minds had to reset.
每学一门语言，我们的大脑都得重置。
Don't get us started on that finance preset, Sandman.
别让我们开始说那个金融预设了，Sandman。
Now on Week 10, my friends asked if I would do it again.
到了第 10 周，我的朋友们问我是否愿意再做一次。
I replied, obviously, because this was CS.
我回答说，当然，因为这是 CS。
No more PSETs, because this was CS Fin.
没有更多的 PSET 了，因为这是 CS50。
Thanks for watching!
感谢收看！